<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title><![CDATA[Initium Lab]]></title>
    <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description><![CDATA[The Website of Initium Lab, the exploratory arm of Initium Media]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 12:06:54 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>http://hexo.io/</generator>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Jackathon #5: Read Journalism]]></title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151005-read-journalism/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151005-read-journalism/</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 11:49:33 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      <![CDATA[<p>We’ll read Journalism books for Jackathon this weekend (October 10th or 11th).</p>
<p>A reading list is compiled with input from within Initium Lab team and our colleagues.<br>Most on the list are in English; some are Chinese.</p>
<p>The reading list covers books about</p>
<ol>
<li>Data Journalism, such as the Verification Handbook for Investigative Reporting, </li>
<li>Human bias, such as Daniel Kahneman’s Thinking: Fast and Slow,</li>
<li>Storytelling, such as Robert McKee’s Story: Substance, Structure, Style and the Principles of Screenwriting,</li>
<li>Writing, such as Stephen King’s On Writing, and</li>
<li>Tradition of Journalism, such as The Elements of Journalism.</li>
</ol>
<p>You’ll read one or more books in one day and share your learning with other participants.</p>
<p>If you like to participate, please fill in the form here: <a href="http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe">http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe</a>.</p>
<p>We’ll check the availability of potential participants and determine the final date, and notify everyone as soon as feasible.</p>
<p>The book list is as follows, categorized by theme.</p>]]>
      
      </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We’ll read Journalism books for Jackathon this weekend (October 10th or 11th).</p>
<p>A reading list is compiled with input from within Initium Lab team and our colleagues.<br>Most on the list are in English; some are Chinese.</p>
<p>The reading list covers books about</p>
<ol>
<li>Data Journalism, such as the Verification Handbook for Investigative Reporting, </li>
<li>Human bias, such as Daniel Kahneman’s Thinking: Fast and Slow,</li>
<li>Storytelling, such as Robert McKee’s Story: Substance, Structure, Style and the Principles of Screenwriting,</li>
<li>Writing, such as Stephen King’s On Writing, and</li>
<li>Tradition of Journalism, such as The Elements of Journalism.</li>
</ol>
<p>You’ll read one or more books in one day and share your learning with other participants.</p>
<p>If you like to participate, please fill in the form here: <a href="http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe" target="_blank" rel="external">http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe</a>.</p>
<p>We’ll check the availability of potential participants and determine the final date, and notify everyone as soon as feasible.</p>
<p>The book list is as follows, categorized by theme.</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<h2 id="Data_Journalism">Data Journalism</h2><h3 id="The_Data_Journalism_Handbook">The Data Journalism Handbook</h3><p>A rich collection of cases demonstrating use of computer and statistical methods in Journalism.</p>
<h3 id="Verification_Handbook_for_Investigative_Reporting">Verification Handbook for Investigative Reporting</h3><p>The book focuses on getting and cleaning data, with emphasis on user-generated information.<br>Availability<br>Free at <a href="http://verificationhandbook.com/book2/chapter1.php" target="_blank" rel="external">http://verificationhandbook.com/book2/chapter1.php</a></p>
<h3 id="Numbers_in_the_newsroom:_using_math_and_statistics_in_News">Numbers in the newsroom: using math and statistics in News</h3><p>The book mainly talks about application of basic Mathematics and Statistics in Journalism.<br>Availability</p>
<h3 id="中国数据新闻工作坊培训手册">中国数据新闻工作坊培训手册</h3><p>(Chinese book)</p>
<p>A compilation of a training workshop which taught the whole flow of Data Journalism.<br>Availability</p>
<p>Freely available at <a href="http://djchina.org/2015/09/01/china-data-journalism-training-content/" target="_blank" rel="external">http://djchina.org/2015/09/01/china-data-journalism-training-content/</a></p>
<h3 id="The_Signal_and_the_Noise">The Signal and the Noise</h3><p>Written by Nate Silver, founder of FiveThirtyEight.com, an icon in Data Journalism. Introduces statistical thinking in daily lifes and the common mistakes made by media people.</p>
<h2 id="Thinking">Thinking</h2><h3 id="A_Tradecraft_Primer:_Structured_Analytic_Techniques_for_Improving_Intelligence_Analysis">A Tradecraft Primer: Structured Analytic Techniques for Improving Intelligence Analysis</h3><p>It introduces the thinking techniques used by Central Intelligence Agency, published by CIA itself. Very practical.</p>
<p>A data journalist is really like an intelligence analyst, who deals with a constant flow of unreliable and contradictory information, needs to deliver insights quickly, and faces pressures to favour certain conclusions.</p>
<p>Freely available at <a href="https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/books-and-monographs/Tradecraft%20Primer-apr09.pdf" target="_blank" rel="external">https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/books-and-monographs/Tradecraft%20Primer-apr09.pdf</a></p>
<h3 id="Rationality:_From_AI_to_Zombies">Rationality: From AI to Zombies</h3><p>For people unfamiliar with cognitive psychology and decision theory, this could be an eye-opener. Written by a AI researcher and is really an edited collection of his blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow_/_思考，快与慢">Thinking, Fast and Slow / 思考，快与慢</h3><p>Detailed introduction into the study of (human) heuristics and biases, i.e., the predictable pattern of our thinking mistakes. The author is a psychologist who won a Nobel Economics prize.</p>
<h3 id="[Supplementary]_Wikipedia:_List_of_Cognitive_Biases">[Supplementary] Wikipedia: List of Cognitive Biases</h3><p>As journalists, it is crucial for us to be aware of our own biases.<br>This is A rather comprehensive list of cognitive biases, most of which have their own Wikipedia pages giving further details.<br>Freely available at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases" target="_blank" rel="external">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases</a></p>
<h2 id="Storytelling">Storytelling</h2><h3 id="Story:_Substance,_Structure,_Style_and_the_Principles_of_Screenwriting">Story: Substance, Structure, Style and the Principles of Screenwriting</h3><p>Principles to make a story compelling from a screenplay writer’s perspective. The book also includes critiques and analysis on movies to illustrate its ideas. An inspiring book for nonfiction writers and journalists who are interested in writing features. </p>
<h3 id="The_Art_and_Craft_of_Feature_Writing:_Based_on_the_Wall_Street_Journal_Guide">The Art and Craft of Feature Writing: Based on the Wall Street Journal Guide</h3><p>A step-by-step guide for turning out great articles. The book provides beginners with a systematic approach to feature writing and new tricks. </p>
<h3 id="Your_Screenplay_Sucks:_100_Ways_to_Make_it_Great">Your Screenplay Sucks: 100 Ways to Make it Great</h3><p>Piecemeal advice about writing good screenplays that sell. May require some basic understanding of the structure and purposes of stories. Highly readable.</p>
<h2 id="Writing">Writing</h2><h3 id="Style:_Lessons_in_Clarity_and_Grace">Style: Lessons in Clarity and Grace</h3><p>A step by step guide to writing correctly and clearly. It is very practical and even somewhat applies to Chinese writing.<br>The older version is better, as they’re free from revisionist tampering.</p>
<h3 id="On_Writing">On Writing</h3><p>Written by Stephen King, an American novelist. This is more a memoir than it’s a textbook, but a substantial part is about use of the English and writing (fiction, mostly).</p>
<h3 id="On_Writing_Well">On Writing Well</h3><p>This is a book for journalism students as well as everyone to learn how to write clearly and elegantly (in English), covering kinds of genres and a wide range of  topics such as people, places, science, tech, business, sports, arts, etc. </p>
<h3 id="Proust_and_the_Squid">Proust and the Squid</h3><p>This book is about the neurology of reading. How exactly does reading work? What can we know about reading from people with Dyslexia (unable to read, but intelligent otherwise) ? </p>
<h2 id="Interviewing_and_Tradition_of_Journalism">Interviewing and Tradition of Journalism</h2><h3 id="在追问中逼近真实">在追问中逼近真实</h3><p>(Chinese book)</p>
<p>Covers basic aspects of reporting about people.</p>
<h3 id="The_Elements_of_Journalism">The Elements of Journalism</h3><p>A comprehensive description of (Western) journalists’ ideas about the core values of Journalism. (Spoiler: it’s “Objectiviy”.)<br>Availability</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151005-read-journalism/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[整日做表沒思路？Google幫你開腦洞]]></title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2015 16:06:19 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      <![CDATA[<p>一個數據分析項目，往往始於摸索一張龐大而陌生的數據表格。嘗試畫些簡易圖表是啟發思路的好辦法，但這絕非易事──想想有多少種圖表：直方圖柱狀圖餅圖折線圖雷達圖……若選取不同的列來分析，每種圖表又有多達幾十種畫法。</p>
<p>Google Sheets 最近推出了一項新功能 Explore，或許能成為探索陌生數據的第一步。Google 介紹稱，Explore 能根據表格內容自動生成盡可能多的圖表，還順帶做些數據分析，挖掘數據的關聯和趨勢[1]。</p>
<p>Explore 的使用方法很簡單，一次點擊就能自動出圖，不時還會附上（它認為）有趣的發現，例如列舉最大值和最小值等。</p>]]>
      
      </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>一個數據分析項目，往往始於摸索一張龐大而陌生的數據表格。嘗試畫些簡易圖表是啟發思路的好辦法，但這絕非易事──想想有多少種圖表：直方圖柱狀圖餅圖折線圖雷達圖……若選取不同的列來分析，每種圖表又有多達幾十種畫法。</p>
<p>Google Sheets 最近推出了一項新功能 Explore，或許能成為探索陌生數據的第一步。Google 介紹稱，Explore 能根據表格內容自動生成盡可能多的圖表，還順帶做些數據分析，挖掘數據的關聯和趨勢[1]。</p>
<p>Explore 的使用方法很簡單，一次點擊就能自動出圖，不時還會附上（它認為）有趣的發現，例如列舉最大值和最小值等。</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<p><img src="/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/explore.gif" alt="Demo of google explore sheet"></p>
<p>但，作為一個每天使用 Google Sheets 超過8小時的人，面對橫空出世的 Explore，欣喜之餘不免有些懷疑，Explore 真的有這麼神？碰巧 Initium Lab 最近出了<a href="http://salary360.initiumlab.com/?from=initiumlab" target="_blank" rel="external">香港工資測試遊戲</a>[2]，遊戲使用 2011 年香港人口普查的公開數據[3]，我從中選取了三張表格來測試 Explore 的實用性。</p>
<h2 id="1-呈現數據：自動選重點出圖">1.呈現數據：自動選重點出圖</h2><p>下圖是一張很常見的表格[4]，要點明確、容易讀懂。Explore 基於表格裏的35項數據自動做出了十張圖，動用了柱狀圖、餅圖、折線圖和堆疊折線圖四種形態。有的圖表下方會出現「一句話總結」，基本都戳中要點。對這種經過預處理的表格而言，Explore 的確能提供不少呈現數據的思路。</p>
<p><img src="/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/pic_1.png" alt="用 Explore 呈現簡單表格的數據"></p>
<h2 id="2-探索數據：幫忙挖掘潛在關聯">2.探索數據：幫忙挖掘潛在關聯</h2><p>一些初看沒什麼亮點的表格，往往藏着大新聞。</p>
<p>我選取的第二個例子[5][6]，統計了香港各區年齡超過65歲的人口比例、慣用廣東話的人口比例和慣用英語的人口比例。一看到這張表，最自然的反應就是，人口年齡和慣用語言之間會不會有關係呢？來看 Explore 有何洞見。</p>
<p>在一秒畫出的十幾張圖表裏，Explore 認為最有趣的發現是，慣用廣東話的人口比例每增加10%，慣用英語的人口比例就會下降7%，這和我們的常識相吻合。雖然在這個例子中 Explore 沒有給出我最想知道的答案，但它兩兩比較了表中的三個變量，幫忙發掘潛在的關聯。</p>
<p><img src="/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/pic_2.png" alt="用 Explore 探索數據潛在的關聯"></p>
<h2 id="3-結構扁平的表格：請和_pivot_table_一起使用">3.結構扁平的表格：請和 pivot table 一起使用</h2><p>處理大批量數據，一般離不開結構扁平的表格，如下圖所示，這類表格信息龐雜、沒有重點。我選取了2011年全港居民的月收入統計來做試驗[7]，這張表格有超過20萬項數據。此時 Explore 就有些力不從心了，它能做的只是發現某列數字的最大或最小值，或是統計不同字符串在某列出現的次數及比例。</p>
<p>在原表格的基礎上做出 pivot table (又稱樞紐分析表，是一種基於原始表格的動態表格，便於將大量的數據集縮小、或分析數據之間的關係) 以後，Explore 能給出新的呈現，做「篩選」和「排序」時，圖表也會實時變化。</p>
<p><img src="/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/pic_3.png" alt="當 Explore 遇到扁平化表格，最好先使用 pivot table 選出要點"></p>
<p>總之，Google Sheets 新功能 Explore 能在最短的時間內羅列出盡可能多的圖表和分析，最適合在探索數據之初，拿來開開腦洞、找找頭緒。</p>
<p>資料來源：<br>[1] <a href="https://support.google.com/docs/answer/6280499?hl=en" target="_blank" rel="external">Quickly get insights on a spreadsheet using Explore</a><br>[2] <a href="http://salary360.initiumlab.com/?from=initiumlab" target="_blank" rel="external">十八區人工大比拼，你份量攞第幾？</a><br>[3] <a href="http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/" target="_blank" rel="external">香港政府統計處 2011香港人口普查</a><br>[4] <a href="http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/main-table/E103.html" target="_blank" rel="external">2001年、2006年及2011年按房屋類型劃分的家庭住戶數目</a><br>[5] <a href="http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/main-table/A301.html" target="_blank" rel="external">2011年按區議會選區及慣用語言劃分的五歲及以上的人口</a><br>[6] <a href="http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/main-table/A303.html" target="_blank" rel="external">2011年按區議會選區、性別及年齡組別劃分的人口</a><br>[7] <a href="http://gazetteer.hk/#/" target="_blank" rel="external">Gazetteer HK</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[React in One Hour]]></title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150925-react-in-1-hour-cuhk/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150925-react-in-1-hour-cuhk/</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 09:02:13 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      <![CDATA[Andy Shu, news engineer with Initium Lab, gave a brief tutorial about ReactJS, the Web UI library from Facebook, in Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK) on 18 September 2015. The event was organized by the Open Innovation Lab of CUHK.]]>
      
      </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Andy Shu, news engineer with Initium Lab, gave a brief tutorial about ReactJS, the Web UI library from Facebook,<br>in Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK) on 18 September 2015. The event was organized by the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/cuhkoil" target="_blank" rel="external">Open Innovation Lab</a> of CUHK.</p>
<p>Andy introduced the basics of React and demonstrated making a simple quiz app from the ground up with React.</p>
<p>Here is the video recoding of the tutorial:</p>
<div class="video-container"><br>    <iframe id="player" type="text/html" width="640" height="390" src="https://youtube.com/embed/_fqf7tGWBvE?html5=1" frameborder="0"><br>    </iframe><br></div>


<p>The video is also available on <a href="http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XMTM0NDg0Mzg5Mg==.html" target="_blank" rel="external">Youku</a>.</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<h2 id="Key_time_points">Key time points</h2><p>00:00 - Introduction to Initium Lab and the Speaker<br>05:02 - What is React<br>16:21 - Necessary packages and tools<br>25:07 - Coding</p>
<p>After the tutorial, a Q&amp;A session was held (not recorded due to technical issues). Afterwards, a few participants stayed for further discussion.</p>
<h2 id="Supporting_Materials">Supporting Materials</h2><p>Please visit <a href="tryreact.initiumlab.com">tryreact.initiumlab.com</a> for supporting materials used in the tutorial, such as the <code>quiz.html</code>, from which you can follow Andy step by step. Intermediate coding samples are also available.</p>
<h2 id="How_to_pick_up_JavaScript">How to pick up JavaScript</h2><p>When asked about how he learnt JavaScript in a short period of time, Andy recommended the <a href="https://www.codecademy.com/tracks/javascript" target="_blank" rel="external">JavaScript track of Codecademy</a> for absolute beginners, <em><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596517748.do" target="_blank" rel="external">JavaScript: The Good Parts</a></em> for a deeper look into the language, and <em><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9781118026694.do" target="_blank" rel="external">Professional JavaScript for Web Developers</a></em> for more comprehensive understanding. He also said frequent practice was crucial to learning. </p>
<h2 id="Errata">Errata</h2><p>Under JavaScript strict mode, <code>this</code> in functions should be <code>undefined</code>, not <code>null</code>.<br>One might have the impression that in the source code, elements like <code>&lt;h1&gt;</code> are just native HTML elements. That is inaccurate. In fact, they are Virtual DOM elements, implemented by React.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150925-react-in-1-hour-cuhk/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Jackathon #3 -- Read a data science book in 8 hours]]></title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 03:57:13 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      <![CDATA[Jackathon is short for “Journalism-Hackathon”. At Initium Lab, we aim to push limits of Journalism with Technology. We hold regular Jackathons to advance our knowledge and skills in using new technology for obtaining data, analysing information, and reporting. This week, the goal for each participant is to read one the the 60 Data Science books collected by KDnuggets within 8 hours. ]]>
      
      </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<video controls poster="/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/jackathon3-timelapse-poster.png"><br>  <source src="/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/jackathon3-timelapse.mp4" type="video/mp4"><br>  <source src="/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/jackathon3-timelapse.webm" type="video/webm"><br>  Sorry, you browser does not support HTML5 video.<br></video>

<p>The video is also available on <a href="https://youtu.be/zFeSh2W1_C8" target="_blank" rel="external">YouTube</a> and <a href="http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XMTM0MzM1MjEwMA==.html?from=y1.7-2" target="_blank" rel="external">Youku</a>.</p>
<h2 id="What_did_we_do?">What did we do?</h2><p>Jackathon is short for “Journalism-Hackathon”. At Initium Lab, we aim to push limits of Journalism with Technology. We hold regular Jackathons to advance our knowledge and skills in using new technology for obtaining data, analysing information, and reporting.</p>
<p>This week, the goal for each participant is to read one the the <a href="http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html" target="_blank" rel="external">60 Data Science books collected by KDnuggets</a> within 8 hours.<br>Participants could pick one or two books to finish reading in 8 hours and present findings / insights to the others.</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<h2 id="What_are_the_books?">What are the books?</h2><p><img src="/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/data-science-books-graph.png" alt="A network of the Data Science books on the recommendation list. A cloud of inter-connected dots"></p>
<p>Fig: Network of 60 books. Blue – book; Red – author; Yellow – key term</p>
<p>We have organised the book list into a structured form and <a href="https://kumu.io/hupili/60-free-data-science-book#60-free-data-science-book" target="_blank" rel="external">visualized the network on kumu.io</a>. Books are associated with authors and terms. Multiple books may share an author or key terms. In this way, books are connected to each other in one way or the other. With graph visualization, we find several clusters:</p>
<ul>
<li>Hard-core machine learning including deep academic results; </li>
<li>Practitioner’s guide including several soft introductory books; and</li>
<li>Those in-between.</li>
</ul>
<p>Every participant of Jackathon #3 finds a suitable book for themselves. For a complete list, you can download <a href="CSV of 60+ data science books: https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1U28nb1z9PsXNzNe_YtfPYYUdhH7_YfjEz6L0Z_wpxzM/edit?usp=sharing">the CSV file</a>.<br>To see how we produces this network visualisation, checkout <a href="https://github.com/hupili/60-data-science-book-visualisation" target="_blank" rel="external">this repo</a>.</p>
<h2 id="Introduction_to_Data_Science">Introduction to Data Science</h2><p>Kate, who was from a non-technical background, picked <em>Introduction to Data Science</em>. The book is useful to equip one with basic Data Science knowledge. The main take-away for Kate was a better understanding of a Data Scientist’s workflow. It turns out that a Data Scientist is not only responsible for “data analysis” but also works on various positions in the whole pipeline including problem identification, data collection, and data visualisation, etc. It is worth noting that this book uses R (a widely used programming language in the Statistics community) to explain Data Science.<br>If you intend to learn R, this book may be a good starting point. Otherwise, you can pick a book using another language (say Python), or a book that is not language dependent.</p>
<h2 id="The_Elements_of_Data_Analytic_Style">The Elements of Data Analytic Style</h2><p>Belinda finds the book <em>The Elements of Data Analytic Style</em> also suitable for beginners. Chapter 3 (on tidying data), are good readings for a Data Scientist’s assistants, while Chapter 9 (on written analysis), teaches useful soft skills. One effective way to read the book is to scan the Table-Of-Content. The ideas are mostly well communicated via section headers. One doesn’t have to read the whole book for the key ideas.</p>
<h2 id="Think_Bayes:_Bayesian_Statistics_Made_Simple">Think Bayes: Bayesian Statistics Made Simple</h2><p>From what Carlson summarises, this book is a practitioner’s guide to statistics. The book deprives lengthy and boring mathematical derivations from a usual first book in statistics and shows you examples/ codes directly. The examples picked in this book is counter-intuitive but demonstrates the power of probability/ statistics knowledge very well. Some well known probability “paradox” includes “Monte Hall problem”, “Locomotive problem” and “Price is Right problem”. The book is case driven. A recommended way of reading is to combine thorough introduction from Wikipedia and code samples from this book.</p>
<h2 id="Think_Stats:_Exploratory_Data_Analysis_in_Python">Think Stats: Exploratory Data Analysis in Python</h2><p>Frank went through <em>Think Stats: Exploratory Data Analysis in Python</em>, written by Allen B. Downey, who also wrote <em>Think Bayes</em>. “If you have never studied statistics, I think this book is a good place to start,” the author said, “And if you have taken a traditional statistics class, I hope this book will help repair the damage.”<br>This book introduces statistical analysis concepts along with Python implementations, including data importing and cleaning, single and multivariable explorations, pair-wise explorations, estimation, and hypothesis testing.<br>If you want to apply your Python skill in data analysis, this book is a practical handbook for you with no redundant words.</p>
<h2 id="Introduction_to_D3">Introduction to D3</h2><p>Andy skimmed two books, <em>D3 Tips and Tricks</em> and <em>Interactive Data Visualization for the Web</em>, as well as the original paper that launched D3. D3 stands for Data-Driven Documents, which is a popular “language” (more precisely a Javascript library) for modern data visualisation in the browser. Andy recommends one start with the paper <em><a href="http://vis.stanford.edu/papers/d3" target="_blank" rel="external">D3: Data Driven Documents</a>,</em>  written by the D3 creator. The paper explains the design rationales behind D3 very well.</p>
<p>As for the two books, <em><a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1230000000345/index.html" target="_blank" rel="external">Interactive Data Visualization for the Web</a> </em> is recommended for beginners because it includes elementary knowledges about HTML all the way to Javascript with a step-by-step guide through the basics of D3. In comparison, <em><a href="https://leanpub.com/D3-Tips-and-Tricks" target="_blank" rel="external">D3 Tips and Tricks</a>,</em>  more akin to a reference book, is recommended for more experienced users.</p>
<p>As a practice, Andy took two hours to make an incomplete imitation of the default visualization of GapMinder (<a href="http://www.gapminder.org" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.gapminder.org</a>) with D3, which illustrated the relationship between wealth and health since 1800. The source code is hosted at <a href="https://github.com/andyshuxin/d3play" target="_blank" rel="external">https://github.com/andyshuxin/d3play</a>.</p>
<h2 id="Natural_Language_Processing_with_Python">Natural Language Processing with Python</h2><p>Ronald have years of experience with image processing and machine learning. He chooses the book <em>Natural Language Processing with Python</em> in order to get some basic knowledge of Natural Language Processing, which may be useful in his recent projects. The book covers NLP principles and practices by showing examples with a Python library called <code>nltk</code>. <code>nlkt</code> is regarded as the defacto standard of NLP in Python, from triping HTML to tokenizing/ tagging sentences. It supports 50+ languages including Chinese. This book is a good fit if you want to deal with unstructured texts.</p>
<h2 id="Social_Media_Mining:_An_Introduction">Social Media Mining: An Introduction</h2><p>This book is compiled from a series of lecture notes, which makes it self-contained. According to Tiffany, “Reading this book is like finishing a whole semester’s course in one day right before final exam”. Before diving into social media mining, the book paves the way by introducing fundamentals of graph theory. There are several widely discussed problems related with graphs and social networks.</p>
<ul>
<li>Network measures. One important concept called “centrality” is used to measure the importance of a node in a network. There are many different metrics that characterise different aspects of importance in a network.</li>
<li>Network models. More precisely speaking, those are called “network generation models”. Say, whether a new node in the network connects to a uniformly random node or picks the node with higher degree? Graphs generated by different models exhibit different characteristics.</li>
<li>Community. Community is group of closely knitted nodes. Discovering community leads to many applications. One example is the book network plotted at the beginning of this blog post. You can easily identify similar books in this way.</li>
<li>Information diffusion. In advertisement scheduling, one can find more effective seed users if the diffusion process is known. There are many models to characterize information diffusion: does the crowd exhibit a herd behaviour? does the adoption probability depend on ratio of existing users (innovation) or not (epidemics)?.. </li>
<li>Influence and homophily. This is the graph theoretic characterisation of the “chicken-and-egg” common knowledge: friends become similar; similar people become friends.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Real-Time_Big_Data_Analytics:_Emerging_Architecture">Real-Time Big Data Analytics: Emerging Architecture</h2><p>Another book read by Belinda is <em>Real-Time Big Data Analytics: Emerging Architecture</em>. This book is more like a guide for executives. It discusses why we need real-time analysis, the challenges, current tool chain and proposed one solution stack. The key objective for real-time analysis is to combine batch and streaming processing. An overview of the proposed architecture reveals four layers. The data layer stores raw data, in heterogeneous or even unstructured format. The analytics layer addresses data buffering and environment (development/ production) isolation issues. The integration layer contains a rule engine and other services that connect data scientists with end users. The decision layer involve end users and provide friendly UI.</p>
<h2 id="References_and_further_readings">References and further readings</h2><ul>
<li>KDnuggets, “60+ Free Books on Big Data, Data Science, Data Mining, Machine Learning, Python, R, and more”, <a href="http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html</a></li>
<li>O’Reilly Atlas Reader, <a href="http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books" target="_blank" rel="external">http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[Legco Matrix Brief (English)]]></title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150916-legco-eng/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150916-legco-eng/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 04:29:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      <![CDATA[We analysed the voting data of the Hong Kong Legislative Council. This is the English version of the motion graphic and digest of the news report.]]>
      
      </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We have promised you an English version of our video about the voting patterns of Hong Kong Legislative Council.<br>And here it is.</p>
<p><video controls poster="/blog/20150916-legco-eng/legco_animation_poster.jpg"><br>  <source src="/blog/20150916-legco-eng/legco_animation_EngSub.mp4" type="video/mp4"><br>  <source src="/blog/20150916-legco-eng/legco_animation_EngSub.webm" type="video/webm"><br>  Sorry, your browser does not support HTML5 video.<br></video><br>The video is also available on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CExoTvKuXSw" target="_blank" rel="external">YouTube</a> and <a href="http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XMTM0MzM5NzQwOA==.html?from=y1.7-1.2" target="_blank" rel="external">Youku</a>.</p>
<p>We also translated the sections of news reports explaining the mysteries mentioned in the video, as follows.</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<h2 id="Why_Starry_Lee_voted_against_herself">Why Starry Lee voted against herself</h2><p>The diagonal shows how each legislator support their own motions. The more supportive they are, the brighter the block. However, there is one outlier on this bright line. Starry Lee Wai-king, chairwoman of Democratic Alliance for the Betterment and Progress of Hong Kong (DAB) and member of the Executive Council, voted against herself 7 times from February 20 to February 21, 2012. During this time, she proposed several amendments to the draft of Stamp Duty Bill but she voted against these amendments herself. Lee replied via her assistant and explained that, she was serving as the president to the committee responsible for revising the bill, and the committee members decided that she, the president, should propose the revisions for them. As DAB opposed those bills, she chose to vote against amendments technically proposed by her.</p>
<h2 id="Why_Poon_Siu-ping_is_more_popular_on_the_opposite_camp">Why Poon Siu-ping is more popular on the opposite camp</h2><p>According to the voting records, no motion amendment from Poon Siu-ping got passed. However, his motion on Occupational Safety, through secret ballot, has been adopted. Poon replied to us that there is no fundamental disagreement between Hong Kong Federation of Trade Unions (FTU) and Federation of Hong Kong and Kowloon Labour Unions (FLU), as FTU is also on pro-establishment camp. However, Poon didn’t think it would be easy to gain FTU’s support: “To improve labour rights and benefits, one has to change the consistently business-oriented operating environment, but many legislators of functional constituency represents business interests and naturally they are unlikely to support motions protecting labour rights.”</p>
<p>Ma Ngok, chairman of Department of Government and Public Administration, Chinese University of Hong Kong, thought pan-democrats have been in mutual restraint since 2012. He said, “First of all, on class position, Civic Party and Democratic Party are moving forward grass-root sector, and they are not much different from the grass-root pan-democracy parties. For instance, a decade ago many pan-democracy parties were doubtful about universal retirement protection, while today all pan-democracy parties support it”. Another reason is the limited power of the Legislative Council. “When debating about grassroot-related motions, which are predictably impossible to pass, many parties would rather follow the trend to avoid controversies”, said Ma.</p>
<p>Ma Ngok explained that,  the reason why Poon Sui-ping, Kwok Wai-keung and Tang Ka-piu were unsupported by pro-establishment camp was probably that functional constituency has long been unwelcoming the labour issues. “Nearly half of the 35 members in functional constituency are in business sector, and some legislators from professional constituencies also tend to business sector. Their attachment to the sector interests makes labour issues hard to gain support.”, said Ma.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150916-legco-eng/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title><![CDATA[可視化火了 盲人怎麼辦]]></title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 13:39:43 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      <![CDATA[作爲新聞人，我們可以怎樣照顧盲人的信息需求呢？]]>
      
      </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/news-related-disabilities.jpg" alt="中國有視力殘障1263萬，香港人口才703萬，上海常住人口1404萬。"><br>中國有五百萬盲人<sup><a href="#note1">[註1]</a></sup>， 接近香港的總人口。 加上弱視，總數超過一千二百萬<sup><a href="#note2">[註2]</a></sup>。</p>
<p>盲人走丟是舊聞，盲貓失蹤纔是新聞：</p>
<ul>
<li>經濟日報：偷貓賊出沒 書店盲貓福仔被盜</li>
<li>文匯報：黑褸賊書局偷盲貓 片段網上瘋傳</li>
<li>東方日報：盲貓「福仔」被尋回　主人喜與愛貓重聚</li>
<li>蘋果日報：被偷5日　疑賊人送往愛協　盲貓「福仔」回家了<br>等等……</li>
</ul>
<a id="more"></a>
<p>盲人也可以用電腦，也會讀新聞。他們看不見，但是聽得到，他們上網用讀屏軟件，屏幕上的字詞，一個個去聽。</p>
<p>現在新聞界，流行信息圖，把大段文字轉化成圖表，方便讀者閱讀。 但正所謂君之蜜糖，彼之砒霜，普通人愛看的信息圖、可視化，對於盲人的讀屏軟件，則是巨大的障礙。</p>
<p>那麼，作爲新聞人，我們可以怎樣照顧盲人的信息需求呢？</p>
<h2 id="盲人怎麼讀新聞">盲人怎麼讀新聞</h2><p>普通人閱讀靠視覺，是「並行」的——你看一眼網頁界面，就知道菜單在哪、內容在哪、哪個是鏈接、哪個可以點。</p>
<p>聽覺是「串行」的，一個盲人如果想「讀完」一個網頁，要讓讀屏軟件從第一個元素（按鈕、菜單選項等）讀起，然後一個一個元素讀下去。</p>
<p>如果想體驗讀屏軟件，在 OS X 或 iPhone 下，可以試用 「VoiceOver」， 這是蘋果內置的讀屏軟件。 閉上眼睛，嘗試一下盲人使用電子產品的方式，試試做一些平常覺得輕而易舉的事情：瀏覽網頁、發發微博，等等。</p>
<p>Windows 可以下載「爭渡讀屏」， Android用戶可以試試內置的Talkback。</p>
<h2 id="給圖像加上詳細的文字描述（alt）">給圖像加上詳細的文字描述（alt）</h2><p>讀屏軟件讀不了數據圖表，於是我們要爲視障讀者撰寫圖像的替代文字描述，具體而言，就是HTML中IMG元素的alt屬性。 對於讀屏軟件的用戶，alt的內容會被完整讀出。</p>
<p>替代說明應該儘可能簡短，但是能夠讓沒有看到圖的讀者都能理解內容。</p>
<p>比如，不要寫「中國GDP數據可視化」，而是寫「中國GDP近年快速增長，2000年爲1.2千億美元，2005年爲2.3千億，2010年爲5.9千億。」</p>
<p>替代說明有個額外的好處：利於搜索引擎處理。搜索引擎蒐集數據，是靠大量「爬蟲」程序，一個網頁一個網頁地檢索內容。爬蟲和盲人一樣，只能「看到」文字，無法閱讀圖像，所以，如果一篇文章的重要信息由圖像呈現，又沒有替代說明，則搜索引擎也看不到這些信息，從而讓用戶更難發現你的文章。</p>
<h2 id="數據可聽化（Sonification）">數據可聽化（Sonification）</h2><p>可聽化是與可視化相似的概念。我們做可視化，是因爲大多數人對數字沒有直覺，難以理解，但是我們對顏色、尺寸、方向有直覺——於是，將數字轉化爲圖像，能夠讓讀者更容易解讀數據。對於依賴聽力的盲人，我們則可以用「可聽化」。</p>
<p>聲音可以操縱的變量有：</p>
<ul>
<li>響度，即大聲還是小聲；</li>
<li>頻率，即高音還是低音；</li>
<li>音色，即泛音的構成；</li>
<li>長度，即很長還是很短。</li>
</ul>
<p>如果將數據與上述一個或幾個變量連接，就能構成一個「可聽化」作品。</p>
<p>一個例子是<a href="http://listen.hatnote.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Listen to Wikipedia</a>。它會實時監測維基百科的改動，然後將每次改動化爲聲音，改動越大，聲音頻率越高；音色代表改動類型——敲擊樂是增訂，絃樂是刪減。這個作品本身對盲人可能用處不大，但是這個技術思路可以用在新聞報道上。</p>
<h2 id="數據可觸化">數據可觸化</h2><p>盲人不止有聽覺，也有觸覺。如果我們將數據化作實際存在的物體，則盲人可以通過觸覺感知。在這個方向，探索的人比較少，偶爾見到零星的嘗試。</p>
<p>比如，西班牙記者 Samuel Granados López <a href="http://cargocollective.com/samuelgranados/Lego-cartogram" target="_blank" rel="external">用樂高積木做過一個地圖</a>，用以標識美洲各國的移民流入、流出量：<br><img src="http://payload230.cargocollective.com/1/14/463324/6918937/IMG_1014.jpg" alt="一塊一人多高的底板，垂直放置。上面用樂高積木拼出了美洲各國，各個國家的突起程度並不相同，移民量越大的國家，越突出。"></p>
<h2 id="展望：數據新聞無障礙">展望：數據新聞無障礙</h2><p>過去，新聞的主要呈現方式是文字，輔以照片、插圖。盲人用了讀屏軟件，也能獲取大部分的信息。</p>
<p>現在，「數據新聞」興起，信息圖、可視化流行，非數據的新聞報道也講求「視覺」「互動」。 </p>
<p>新聞人考慮的大多是報道網頁在手機上能不能看、用觸屏好不好控制，不太考慮盲人用戶能否閱讀、色盲用戶會否迷惑、殘障用戶能否使用。</p>
<p>我們在呈現方式上發足狂奔之時，不應該忽略少數有特別需求的用戶。 有的用戶看不到屏幕、有的用戶用不了鼠標，他們仍然有信息需求，仍然可以是我們的讀者。 </p>
<p>我們在製作每條新聞報道的時候，不止要考慮如何讓大多數用戶迅速理解，也要考慮如何保證每個用戶對新聞內容能有最基本的了解。<br>從今天開始，請給你的信息圖加上alt吧！</p>
<p><strong>數據來源</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><a name="note1"></a> <a href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs230/en/" target="_blank" rel="external">世界衛生組織</a></li>
<li><a name="note2"></a> <a href="http://www.zgmx.org.cn/html/default/4/NewsDefault-47618.html" target="_blank" rel="external">中國盲人協會</a></li>
<li>殘疾人口數據來自： <a href="http://www.cdpf.org.cn/sjzx/cjrgk/201206/t20120626_387581.shtml" target="_blank" rel="external">殘疾人聯合會</a></li>
<li>上海人口數據來自： <a href="http://www.shrkjsw.gov.cn/dr/stat/ssh/2011823/000000003500041001134458916.html" target="_blank" rel="external">上海市人口和計劃生育委員會</a></li>
<li>香港人口數據來自： <a href="http://www.censtatd.gov.hk/hkstat/sub/sp150.jsp?productCode=B1120017" target="_blank" rel="external">香港政府統計處</a></li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
