<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Initium Lab</title>
    <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    
    <description>The Website of Initium Lab, the exploratory arm of Initium Media</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 08:16:09 GMT</pubDate>
    <generator>http://hexo.io/</generator>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jackathon #7 Data Hacking</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151130-Jackathon-7/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151130-Jackathon-7/</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 04:08:48 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        We hacked on two datasets on Nov 7, 2015.
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This week’s theme is “hacking data”, on which Initium Lab, with 6 friends invited, tried to analyze or visualize two data sets and produce meaningful presentations. We introduced two of our own data sets to participants: 1) structured data of CCTV news broadcast; 2) structured data of HK Research Grant Council (RGC), which Initium Lab had made some simple processing in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former one was crawled from CCTV’s website, consisting of  news scripts said by the anchors of CCTV’s daily news broadcast from 2011 to 2015. The latter was crawled from Hong Kong Research Grants Council’s (RGC) website, including all funded projects with their detailed information, among 8 institutions in Hong Kong in recent 10 years. Participants could pick one of the data sets and any works related to Data Journalism were welcomed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Idea-Brainstorm&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Idea-Brainstorm&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Idea Brainstorm&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Idea Brainstorm&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started with a brainstorm in which participants made lively discussions and showed their great interest in the two data sets we offered. Inspired by stock market prediction, Carlson Zhuo, one of our guests who is from the Chinese University of Hong Kong, came out of the idea of making political prediction by analyzing CCTV news. Chao Tianyi, researcher with Initium Lab, said we could analyze how death events were reported on CCTV. As for RGC data set, Andy Shu, our front-end engineer and editor suggested investigating the most funded professors, etc. After this fruitful brainstorm, we started the Jackathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151130-Jackathon-7/all_people.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jackathoning together&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;What-Are-the-Fruits&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#What-Are-the-Fruits&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;What Are the Fruits?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Are the Fruits?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;About-CCTV-Data-Set&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#About-CCTV-Data-Set&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;About CCTV Data Set&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;About CCTV Data Set&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We made several pretty interesting outputs with this data set. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy created a Xinwenlianbo (CCTV News Simulcast) search engine in nearly 5 hours. Using this search engine one can search how many times a keyword is mentioned in the CCTV data set. It displays the results in the form of bar chart along with numbers. For example, if we want to know how many times “计划生育” (Family Planning in China) appeared in CCTV news recent years, we can search for keyword “计划生育” and see the result. Andy explained that the number only represented number of news reports rather than that of words, i.e. if a word appeared many times in one piece of news, it will only count as “1”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151130-Jackathon-7/xinwenlianbo_family_plan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Searching result of “计划生育” in Xinwenlianbo&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fig: Searching result of “计划生育”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve got a search engine, then what did we find? There is a funny joke about CCTV news spreading over the Internet in China, that is “ CCTV daily news tells but three things: busy leaders, happy Chinese and suffering foreigners.” Playing with data Victoria Jin and Yan Rong, a student from Hong Kong Baptist University, found evidence to support the view. They found headlines related to “busy leaders” covered 30% of the whole CCTV news data. In addition, positive words were usually used on China and Chinese people, whereas foreign countries and foreigners were usually accompanied by negative words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151130-Jackathon-7/xinwenlianbo_types.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ratio of types in CCTV News&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fig: Rows-Total, Disaster, Happened, Attacked, Conflict, Turbulence, Loss, Failed. Columns-All news, International news, Ratio. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonnie Wang, also a student from Hong Kong Baptist University, analyzed different tones on special days, including Chinese Spring Festival and Tomb-sweeping Day. She found that CCTV would like to use more positive words than negative ones on these two days, which has verified her assumption in the brainstorm section. Carlson tried to see whether we can use CCTV news data to predict national policy and stock market. And Chaotian studied how great people’s death were reported and  counted their frequency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151130-Jackathon-7/passed_away.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Usage frequency of “逝世” (passed away) of different people&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;Fig: Usage frequency of “逝世” (passed away).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;About-RGC-Data-Set&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#About-RGC-Data-Set&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;About RGC Data Set&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;About RGC Data Set&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As for RGC data set, we also made some interesting discoveries. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serina Xu, a PhD student in Computer Science department of  The University of Hong Kong, made a collaborators graph to see potential collaborations among scholars in The University of Hong Kong. She visualized her data with KUMU and found that more outstanding schools usually showed more cooperation. Besides, it is professors who usually sit at the cross center surrounded by several doctors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ronald Tse, who is from The Chinese University of Hong Kong, visualized the performance indicator of different universities with couple of indicators and also the efficiency. He used some specific measurements to evaluate scholars  who have had obtained the highest fund, and their outputs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edited by Liu Xue&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151130-Jackathon-7/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The First PyCon in Hong Kong - PyCon HK 2015</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151119-The-First-PyCon-in-Hong-Kong-PyCon-HK-2015/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151119-The-First-PyCon-in-Hong-Kong-PyCon-HK-2015/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 04:08:48 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        On 7 Nov 2015 and 8 Nov 2015, PyCon (Python Conference) was held at Hong Kong Cyberport. It is the largest annual gathering for the Pythoners community. Python is one our most commonly used languages at Initium Lab so we definitely did not miss the chance. Two Initium Lab members, Pili Hu and Andy Xin, gave talks about scraping on the conference. Following are the quick and short notes we took away from PyConHK 2015.
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;On 7 Nov 2015 and 8 Nov 2015, PyCon (Python Conference) was held at Hong Kong Cyberport. It is the largest annual gathering for the Pythoners community. Python is one our most commonly used languages at Initium Lab so we definitely did not miss the chance. Two Initium Lab members, Pili Hu and Andy Xin, gave talks about scraping on the conference. Following are the quick and short notes we took away from PyConHK 2015. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151119-The-First-PyCon-in-Hong-Kong-PyCon-HK-2015/pycon-hk-2015.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MOU PyConHK. Photo Credit: PyConHK Facebook Group&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Photo Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/pyconhk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;PyConHK Facebook Group&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Python-and-PyCon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Python-and-PyCon&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Python and PyCon&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Python and PyCon&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For those who do not know Python, it is a programming language that let you work quickly and efficiently. However, PyCon is not only about Python, it is more about the open ecosystem and its supportive community. Therefore, this conference is dedicated to provide enjoyable experience to almost everyone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Topics-included&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Topics-included&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Topics included&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Topics included&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because diversity is one of PyCon’s enshrined spirits, a broad range of topics were covered by speakers from different fields including search engine, text mining, data science techniques, web development, financial technology, alternative language, just to name a few. For a full list of topics presented on PyCon, you can refer to the conference’s official website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://2015.pycon.hk/schedule/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://2015.pycon.hk/schedule/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following are some of selected topics that we would like to share with the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Elasticsearch-talks-and-workshop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Elasticsearch-talks-and-workshop&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Elasticsearch talks and workshop&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Elasticsearch talks and workshop&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Honza Král from Elastic Co.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elastic Co. is the one of the conference’s Gold Sponsors and its speaker was very contributory by giving two talks and one workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explore your data with Elasticsearch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;The first topic given by Mr. Honza Král is ‘Explore your data with Elasticsearch’. We can outline it into the following parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He explained Elasticsearch as a document based distributed search engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full-text search means you can search unstructured text in or across field. It also allows fuzzy search. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Under the hood, the principle is bible concordance and inverted index. For example, you can think it as an index at the back of the book which tells us which word appears at which pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When building a index, text are normally split into words. Some words will be chopped to enable fuzzy search. e.g. &lt;code&gt;encourage&lt;/code&gt; can be chopped into &lt;code&gt;encourag&lt;/code&gt;, therefore, when you search &lt;code&gt;encouraging&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;encourage&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;encouragement&lt;/code&gt; can still be included in search result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merging sorted lists enable distributability and flexibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aggregations: count, sum, avg, min, max, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most languages are supported. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use all your Logs!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;The second topic is a demonstration of how to utilise logs generated from customer transactions or your servers. For example, you may probably setup a website for people to visit. You may wonder what are those people looking at, or what are they doing there. A simple way to answer those questions is to use &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; to check your log files. However, this way could fall apart quickly because - as the size of logs growing - you will end up with multiple logs on multiple machines. Of course it is not possible for you to check each individual record. Hence, It is better to have a overview, analysis and visualisation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt; have other problems. A typical scenario is that you may want to investigation what happened at a particular time. Unfortunately, different software may generate logs with different time format. This stops you from checking correlated events.  So it is ideal have a central storage for all your logs. You can also enrich the data there. Take IP address for example, those address can be converted into hostname and locations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Král later recommended the follow steps to use ELK for your logs: collect, parse, enrich, store, search, aggregate and visualise. ELK is a collection of open source tools, namely, elasticsearch, logstash and kibana. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logstash is mainly responsible for data injection pipeline. It has all the necessary utilities to collect, parse and enrich data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elasticsearch have nice features to store, aggregate and search data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kibana, the most impressive and technologically the most simple part, which is for visualisation. It communicate with elasticsearch and provide you with gorgeous charts and pictures. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workshop: Don’t be afraid to search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;The workshop was to write real Python code using elasticsearch_dsl package to interact with Elasticsearch. Before the workshop, he created a simple website using Django and data from StackExchange dumps (&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/stackexchange&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://archive.org/details/stackexchange&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task of the workshop:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add a solid search implementation to the website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the workshop, Mr. Král covered basic steps like syncing the models to a search engine and setting up search views, as well as some more advanced functionality such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;faceted navigation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tolerance for spelling mistake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommandation according to relevancy and popularity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search with synonyms.    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can checkout the code of the workshop from - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/HonzaKral/es-django-example&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/HonzaKral/es-django-example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;What-exactly-is-‘plastics’-on-Hong-Kong-Golden-Forum-A-text-mining-analysis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#What-exactly-is-‘plastics’-on-Hong-Kong-Golden-Forum-A-text-mining-analysis&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;What exactly is ‘plastics’ on Hong Kong Golden Forum? A text mining analysis&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What exactly is ‘plastics’ on Hong Kong Golden Forum? A text mining analysis&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Chung-hong Chan (電鋸)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Chan is a Phd student from Journalism and Media Studies Centre, The University of Hong Kong. With a combination of different tools in python and perl, he applied a classic topic model analysis to the text in Golden Forum. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tools and method he used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selenium - It is a suite of tools to automate web browsers across many platforms. Selenium was used because Golden Forum did not allow scraping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GNU Parallel - A command line drive utility for Unix-like operating systems to execute scripts in parallel. Mr. Chan used this to run multiple selenium instances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jieba - Tokenization of forum text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘Big data is small data’. He said his laptop is old, therefore, he only extract data he thought useful to his analysis. Combination of features to get better features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LDA - The full name is Latent Dirichlet allocation, a model for topic discovery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small tools that do one thing better is superior than one tool that do everything poorly. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Monitoring-the-performance-of-Python-web-applications&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Monitoring-the-performance-of-Python-web-applications&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Monitoring the performance of Python web applications&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Monitoring the performance of Python web applications&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Graham Dumpleton from Red Hat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is the author of &lt;code&gt;mod_wsgi&lt;/code&gt;. In this talk, he told us how the performance of traditional Python web application can be measured in detail. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common method in measuring &lt;code&gt;WSGI&lt;/code&gt; application’s response time is to use &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; statements. This is okay for when playing around in a development environment to understand how a WSGI server works, but it is totally inadequate when wanting to monitor traffic against a real website. According to Graham, a better approach would be to implement monitoring in the WSGI server level using event notifications. In this way, the specific code dealing with requests in the WSGI server can simply be enhanced to track information in any existing context where the information is already available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various monitoring capabilities have been implemented for &lt;code&gt;mod_wsgi&lt;/code&gt;, including at the Apache server level, worker/daemon process level. But unfortunately, this no timeline as to when these capabilities will be made available in any official release of &lt;code&gt;mod_wsgi&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further details, you can read Graham Dumpleton’s blog posts at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dscpl.com.au/2015/05/performance-monitoring-of-real-wsgi.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://blog.dscpl.com.au/2015/05/performance-monitoring-of-real-wsgi.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.dscpl.com.au/2015/06/implementing-request-monitoring-within.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://blog.dscpl.com.au/2015/06/implementing-request-monitoring-within.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Using-Python-for-data-mining-projects&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Using-Python-for-data-mining-projects&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Using Python for data mining projects&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Using Python for data mining projects&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Chris Choy &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Choy is profession in statistics and data mining. He got his Phd in high dimensional statistic in Oxford and is now a Senior Computational Scientist at ClusterTech. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, he demonstrated a simple scenario to use a combination of Python packages, e.g. Jupyter notebook, SQLAlchemy, Pandas, statsmodel, to rapidly workout data mining solutions on flight data. The problem he try to solve is: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During all 7 days in a week, in which day is the flights more incline to be delayed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How he used those tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/strong&gt; - Easily reflected database scheme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pandas&lt;/strong&gt; - Convert sql data into data frame which is useful in representing 2-dimensional labeled data structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statsmodel&lt;/strong&gt; - Applied &lt;code&gt;OLS&lt;/code&gt; (ordinary least squares) regession model to dataframes in one line code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patsy&lt;/strong&gt; - Design matrix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matplotlib&lt;/strong&gt; - Plot a chart of the regression result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the code can be found on his github repository:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/christlc/pycon2015hk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/christlc/pycon2015hk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;My-personal-take&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#My-personal-take&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;My personal take&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;My personal take&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Austin Imperial (Niknok), 13 years old&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yea, it is not a typo, a 13-year-old coding machine did spoke in this Conference. He is a Grade 8 student from the Philippines. He studied Python, PHP, Ruby, Javascript, C, C++, SQL, HTML and CSS from MOOC (Massive Open Online Course) on him own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two courses that he studied:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computer Science, Harvard University&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Introduction to the intellectual enterprises of computer science and the art of programming. This course teaches students how to think algorithmically and solve problems efficiently. Topics include abstraction, algorithms, data structures, encapsulation, resource management, security, software engineering, and web development. Languages include C, PHP, and JavaScript plus SQL, CSS, and HTML. Problem sets inspired by real-world domains of biology, cryptography, finance, forensics, and gaming. Designed for concentrators and non-concentrators alike, with or without prior programming experience. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs50.harvard.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://cs50.harvard.edu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python, Rice University&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;This two-part course is designed to help students with very little or no computing background learn the basics of building simple interactive applications. The language of choice, Python, is an easy-to learn, high-level computer language that is used in many of the computational courses offered on Coursera. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Austin Imperial classified codes into three types: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 1&lt;/strong&gt; - Code that is useful to both the society and self.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 2&lt;/strong&gt; - Code that is useless to the the society, but useful to self because it still enhance the programmer’s coding skill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type 3&lt;/strong&gt; -  Code that neither the society nor self would benefit from and is total waste of time and effort, but still entertaining at the very least especially when you are starting to explore the basics (e.g. print “hello world”) of what you have learned. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said a Python beginner should focus on doing a project based on 1st and 2nd type of code but try NOT to stay away from 3rd type of code because it may still give you terrific idea of not doing IT the second time around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Austin do have insightful opinions in creating personal projects. He said in order to make a personal project, you need to have the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idea&lt;/strong&gt; - come from boredom, another project, techniques that you have learned, daydream, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define the Problem&lt;/strong&gt; - could be from daily life, e.g. family members blood pressure records.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find a Solution&lt;/strong&gt; - common sense, consult others, think like a machine, simplifying another existing problem, apply past solutions, sleep on the problem and set aside temporarily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inspiration&lt;/strong&gt; - needs of your life, other people’s projects; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He summarised that personal projects depends on different variables, input of ideas, your interest, even your mood has a great impact on your future code/project. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His github: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/akaNiknok&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/akaNiknok&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Introduction-to-aiohttp-–-asyncio-based-web-framework&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Introduction-to-aiohttp-–-asyncio-based-web-framework&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Introduction to aiohttp – asyncio-based web framework&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Introduction to aiohttp – asyncio-based web framework&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Andrew Svetlov&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is talk given by the author of the &lt;code&gt;aiohttp&lt;/code&gt; framework. As Austin Imperial - the speaker of ‘My Personal Take’ - have mentioned,  inspiration can be a need to solve a problem in your life. &lt;code&gt;aiohttp&lt;/code&gt; is to solve the common problem that faced by most programmers who write asynchronous web application. If you have experience in Node.js,  it is quite common to encounter non-elegant code with infinite callbacks. The same type of problem also appears in Python. Programmer need to adopt asynchronous programming when a lot of I/O is involved. This is because I/O is slow and the CPU is not needed to handle most of it. So Python’s creator mentioned, in PyCon 2013, that he was working on a ‘standard framework’ to standardize the event loop. The framework is &lt;code&gt;asyncio&lt;/code&gt; and enable us to run asynchronous computations without callbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Svetlov said that &lt;code&gt;aiohttp&lt;/code&gt; is a HTTP client/server built on top of asyncio. It allows you to write programmer friendly code like well-known linear one but utilizes the power of nonblocking sockets and supports websockets natively. He divided his talk into several part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic introduction of coroutine and future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debugging is much more easier with explicit loop and &lt;code&gt;PYTHONASYNCIODEBUG=1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to write a asynchronous http client.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a trivial http server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use static routing, web-sockets, middlewares and debugtoolbar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make asynchronous request use &lt;code&gt;aiohttp&lt;/code&gt;‘s client library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flow control in transport / protocol level and streams level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;event loop basics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;aiopg&lt;/code&gt;: accessing postgresql database from the &lt;code&gt;asyncio&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;comparison with other asynchronous libraries such twists and tornado.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also noted that async code forces all your code to be async. That means you should not use sync call which may tale a while for execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please refer to his github for more information: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/asvetlov&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/asvetlov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docs: &lt;a href=&quot;http://aiohttp.readthedocs.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://aiohttp.readthedocs.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source code: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/KeepSafe/aiohttp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/KeepSafe/aiohttp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is happy to accept pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Better-type-at-Python&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Better-type-at-Python&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Better type at Python&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Better type at Python&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;:  Rick Mak from Oursky &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Function annotation is Python 3.5’s new feature. It is useful for static type analysis, e.g. type hints in a IDE, discover bugs earlier. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a simple function whose argument and return type are declared in the annotations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight python&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;function&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;greeting&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;(name: str)&lt;/span&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&#39;Hello &#39;&lt;/span&gt; + name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr Mak is an advocate for using type annotations. Although this feature do not help your code gain performance boost, it provides the following benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type Hints&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type checkers can easily detect that you maybe passing an object with a type that is not expected.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other person who read your code will know what is expected and how to use it without getting a &lt;code&gt;TypeError&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IDE will suggest appropriate methods when know what type your object is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Static Type Checkers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find bugs sooner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help the maintenance of large project less painful. The bigger your application becomes the more control and predictability you require.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large teams are already running static analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow Mr. Mak at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rickmak&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/rickmak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Workshop-Let’s-break-some-stupid-CAPTCHAs&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Workshop-Let’s-break-some-stupid-CAPTCHAs&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Workshop: Let’s break some stupid CAPTCHAs!&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Workshop: Let’s break some stupid CAPTCHAs!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Chung-hong Chan （電鋸）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chung-hong Chan demonstrated how to crack stupid CAPTCHAS. Python libraries such as Numpy, Matplotlib, and OpenCV were introduced. The most amazing thing we could learn from this workshop was that so many CAPTCHAS on Hong Kong websites are REALLY weak, for example, some even expose raw answers in HTML page source.&lt;br&gt;Source code Chung-hong Chan demonstrated could be found on his GitHub repo for PyCon: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/chainsawriot/pycon_vm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/chainsawriot/pycon_vm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Financial-technology&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Financial-technology&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Financial technology&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Financial technology&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Joseph Wang (joequant) from Bitquant Research Laboratories&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Joseph Wang is chief scientist of Bitquant Research Laboratories, a small Hong Kong-based financial technology company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Dr. Wang, Python is intensively used in investment banking. What’s more, large parts of the Python infrastructure were funded by banks. However, why it isn’t well-known in the Python community? Because banks have no reason to share their algorithm to competitors, and they don’t want regulators and patent trolls knowing what they are doing as well.&lt;br&gt;Dr. Wang was currently working on his trading bot project. “Trading is 90% psychology,“ Dr. Wang said, “Go to a casino, see what people do, and don’t do that.”&lt;br&gt;Dr. Wang encouraged audience to “steal my software please!!!” You must be interested to get something on his GitHub at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/joequant/bitquant&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/joequant/bitquant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Decoding-the-language-of-cereal-box-Design-with-Scikit-Learn&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Decoding-the-language-of-cereal-box-Design-with-Scikit-Learn&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Decoding the language of cereal box Design with Scikit-Learn&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Decoding the language of cereal box Design with Scikit-Learn&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Mart van de Ven (tijptjik)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk is about find correlation between the cartoon brands on the cereal boxes and what’s inside the cereal boxes. Mart uses a set of data science techniques to explore how marketing departments use colour, layout and character design to communicate what you can expect from a cereal. He in this talk highlighted the use of the PyData stack to generate features from images, cluster cereal types and predict their nutritional values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps he used to define and solve data science problems: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask an interesting question, e.g. what is the correlation between the cartoon images and the cereals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the data, namely, the images of the cartoon on those cereal boxes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore the data. Try to check what can be extract by Human and what can be recognised by computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model the data. According to the data explored, model your data. For this case, color, brands, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally communicate and visualise the result. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mart’s work train. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparing the data. He used cv2 library to get feature vectors from raw images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight python&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; cv2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;cv2.imread(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&#39;cerealbox.png&#39;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then clean the feature vectors. e.g. get rid of white colour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight python&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;cv2.threshold(img...)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read values, including dimensions, grayscale histogram, flattened color histogram, resize the picture, RGB to HSV, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine learning: Hair features, Haar cascade, Gaze recognition…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about this talk, you can contact him by email m@droste.hk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Scraping-the-web&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Scraping-the-web&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Scraping the web&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Scraping the web&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scraping is an important part of data journalism and we perform scraping regularly at Initium Lab.&lt;br&gt;Two members from Initium Lab shared their experience on scraping at PyConHK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andy Shu, News Engineer @ Initium Lab – Scraping in 5 min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pili Hu, Data Scientist @ Initium Lab – Scrape more with Less codes &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the lightning talk, Andy introduced his experience on scraping in 5 minutes.&lt;br&gt;Apparently, one can not learn scraping from zero to one just in 5 minutes, especially starting with non-technical background. Nevertheless, Andy’s talk helps one build the concept of scraping and understand common caveats in the process. Interested readers can refer to the slides: &lt;a href=&quot;http://slides.com/andyshuxin/s#/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://slides.com/andyshuxin/s#/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pili’s talk is devoted to quick scraping with the help of some utility tools and Python libraries.&lt;br&gt;When doing data journalism, one would iterate between the steps for multiple rounds, from scraping to analysis, to visualisation, and all the way to story-telling. You never want to spend a large chunk of time building a rigorous scraper and ends up in an unpublishable report because of lack of insights, lack of story, lack of evidence from data, … At the very early proof-of-concept stage, quick scraping skills help one to validate the idea with least cost and that is the focus of the talk. The tools shared in this talk include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human friendly HTTP interface:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLI: &lt;code&gt;HTTPie&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python REPL: &lt;code&gt;requests&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale-out:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLI:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single machine: &lt;code&gt;xargs -P&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple machine: &lt;code&gt;pssh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python REPL:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better to wrap as individual scripts and do multi process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manual parse:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLI: &lt;code&gt;pQuery&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python REPL:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;pyQuery&lt;/code&gt; for FE people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt; useful for tabulared data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic parse, in Python REPL:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;PyReadability&lt;/code&gt;: Parse the main body of a page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;scraply&lt;/code&gt;: Learn patterns from your labelling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested readers can refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://project.hupili.net/workshop-easy-scraping/Scrape%20More%20with%20Less%20Codes.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;IPython Notebook of the talk&lt;/a&gt;. ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hupili/workshop-easy-scraping/blob/master/Scrape%20More%20with%20Less%20Codes.ipynb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Haxe-a-statically-typed-language-that-compiles-to-Python&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Haxe-a-statically-typed-language-that-compiles-to-Python&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Haxe, a statically-typed language that compiles to Python&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Haxe, a statically-typed language that compiles to Python&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Andy Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have mentioned that PyCon is not only for Python, it is a gathering welcomes diversity. So here comes a talk about another programming languages, Haxe. Haxe is an open source high-level multi-platform programming language and compiler that can produce application and source code for 9 platforms. Here is a list of compiler targets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flash - into byte code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neko - into byte code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript - into source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ActionScript 3 - into source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHP - into source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C++ - into source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java - into source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C# - into source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python - into source code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haxe’ features: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript / Java style syntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;static typing with type inference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Object-Oriented programming paradigm &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functional programming paradigm: list comprehension, option, pattern matching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haxe advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No need to use new language when trying new things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code reuse of business logic part.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test all languages with your own app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Static typing catches errors earlier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type annotation is one kind of documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Static typing leads to better code generation and even better performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haxe to Python sample:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haxe code&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight haxe&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;class&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Untyped&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;function&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;type&quot;&gt;: Void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; l = &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;untyped&lt;/span&gt; list(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;abc&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;trace&lt;/span&gt;(l); &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;// [&#39;a&#39;, &#39;b&#39;, &#39;c&#39;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    &amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python code&lt;/strong&gt; generated&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight python&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;class&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Untyped&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    __slots__ = ()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;decorator&quot;&gt;    @staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;function&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        l = list(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;abc&quot;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        print(str(l))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future work in relation to Python target:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Output type annotations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Release Haxe libs to pypi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-implement python api in Haxe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find Andy’s slides HERE: &lt;a href=&quot;http://haxe.io/@andy_li/PyCon%20HK%202015.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://haxe.io/@andy_li/PyCon%20HK%202015.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-changing-landscape-of-Python-web-application-deployment&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-changing-landscape-of-Python-web-application-deployment&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The changing landscape of Python web application deployment&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The changing landscape of Python web application deployment&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Graham Dumpleton &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is another talk from Graham, the author of &lt;code&gt;mod_wsgi&lt;/code&gt;. He is now working for the Red Hat’s OpenShift team, a PaaS (Platform-as-a-Server) solution that allows developers to quickly develop, host and scale applications in cloud environment. He said the reason that he become part of the OpenShift team is because Red Hat announced the intention to bring Docker and Kubernetes together and overhaul OpenShift to be fully based around these technologies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, Graham made a comparison between Containers and Virtual Machines.  Unlike a Virtual Machine, using a Container do not require an virtualisation of physical hardware. So the main benefit that you will gain from Containers based technology is its lower overhead and potentially better performance. Then, he introduced Docker, which is all about making it easier to create, deploy and run applications by using containers.  Accordingly to Graham, Docker can make Python web hosting better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no slides for this talk, but he did show us several tricks in using Docker. I list two of them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build a data only container&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight dockerfile&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;//Dockerfile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt; busybox&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;RUN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;mkdir /data &amp;amp;&amp;amp; chown www-data /data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;VOLUME&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;//Commands&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker build -t data-only-container .&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -name data-only data-only-container true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker ps -a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -rm -it -u 33 --volumes-&lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; data-only busybox sh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;cd /data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;date &amp;gt; date.txt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;cat date.txt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -rm -it -u 33 -volumes-&lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; data-only busybox sh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker inspect data-only | less&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;the physical location&amp;#125; /mnt/ .  Mount: &amp;#123;&amp;#125;..&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker commit live-data live-data-only&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker images&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; --rm -it live-data-only sh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -it busybox sh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -rm -it manual-created sh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build a simple python web application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight dockerfile&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;//Dockerfile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt; python:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2.7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;USER&lt;/span&gt; $MOD_WSGI_USER: $MOD_WSGI_GROUP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -rm -p 8000:80 python-app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;curl http://&amp;#123;docker-ip&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -rm -p 8000:80 --name ..&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;docker &lt;span class=&quot;built_ins&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt; -rm -link .. &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;# connect two containers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Closing&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Closing&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Closing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Closing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are more topics that we do not cover in this notes. But we believe it evidenced that the Python community is vast, diverse and open. Actually, PyCon HK 2015 is only the tip of an iceberg. At the closing stage of the conference, we had PyCon organisers from both Taiwan and Korea give us lightening talks. Yep, they are preparing PyCon TW &amp;amp; PyCon APAC 2016. &lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151119-The-First-PyCon-in-Hong-Kong-PyCon-HK-2015/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hong Kong Code Conf 2015</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151112-Hong-Kong-Code-Conf-2015/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151112-Hong-Kong-Code-Conf-2015/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2015 15:41:46 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        Summary of the Talks in Hong Kong Code Conf 2015
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hongkong.codeconf.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Hong Kong Code Conf 2015&lt;/a&gt; was held on 24 October 2015. I (Andy Shu) participated in most sections and here is my notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Death-by-Bad-API-Design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Death-by-Bad-API-Design&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Death by Bad API Design&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Death by Bad API Design&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Matthew Rudy Jacobs from Go Go Van&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew stresses that for compatiblity reasons, APIs don’t die; hence, good API design is important.ce&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His solution is to design API first, rather than as an afterthought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design workflow is as follows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write API docs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull-request API docs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also gave advices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anticipate changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t add spelling mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t add API depending on the implementation quirks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He mentioned a few pointers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apiary.io/blueprint&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://apiary.io/blueprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://swagger.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://swagger.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jsonapi.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://jsonapi.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/RESTful-Web-APIs-Leonard-Richardson/dp/1449358063&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://www.amazon.com/RESTful-Web-APIs-Leonard-Richardson/dp/1449358063&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;The-Path-to-Continuous-Delivery&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Path-to-Continuous-Delivery&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Path to Continuous Delivery&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Path to Continuous Delivery&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Pedro Pimentel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Core-practices&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Core-practices&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Core practices&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Core practices&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;BDD&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#BDD&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;BDD&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;BDD&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start with User story&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an &lt;em&gt;__&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to &lt;em&gt;__&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So that &lt;em&gt;__&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;TDD&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#TDD&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;TDD&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;TDD&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write just enough to pass the test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read tests to learn about someone else’s code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assert first&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One assertion per test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faking/Stubbing/Mocking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pair Programming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pair rotation (so that any two programmers have chance to cooperate)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some pointers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://manifesto.softwarecraftsmanship.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://manifesto.softwarecraftsmanship.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cucumber.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://cucumber.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous Delivery by Jez Humble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Phoenix Project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Scraping&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Scraping&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Scraping&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Scraping&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vincent Lau and Elaine Chan talked about their experiences scraping the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides are available here:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1gmDWYHYRcG1u8iR5suNqEw8iBtYxQNG18ssqVhclk3I/edit#slide=id.p&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1gmDWYHYRcG1u8iR5suNqEw8iBtYxQNG18ssqVhclk3I/edit#slide=id.p&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slides are noticably better than my notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Casandra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frontera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s4/sh/74125b92-70d7-497d-8013-68f17f996e22/96be3fb18f2bbc20&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s4/sh/74125b92-70d7-497d-8013-68f17f996e22/96be3fb18f2bbc20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Your-Front-End-Performance-Sucks&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Your-Front-End-Performance-Sucks&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Your Front End Performance Sucks&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Your Front End Performance Sucks&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Holger Bartel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance is Design&lt;br&gt;Design is Performance&lt;br&gt;Design directs performance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Images - The Big Evil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ImageOptim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimise the Critical Rendering === Get stuff on the screen fast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimise the number of critical resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;minimise the number of critical bytes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;minitise the critical path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay special attention to critical resources, i.e. the blocking resrouces&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://httparchive.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://httparchive.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://webpagetest.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://webpagetest.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tools.pingdom.com/fpt&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://tools.pingdom.com/fpt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/speed/pagespeed/insights/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Google Pagespeed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.yahoo.com/yslow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://developer.yahoo.com/yslow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://perf-tooling.today&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://perf-tooling.today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning about performance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://perf.rocks&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Perf.rocks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/bevacqua/perfschool&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;PerfSchool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Decoding-the-Language-of-Cereal-Box-Design-with-Scikit-Learn&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Decoding-the-Language-of-Cereal-Box-Design-with-Scikit-Learn&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Decoding the Language of Cereal Box Design with Scikit-Learn&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Decoding the Language of Cereal Box Design with Scikit-Learn&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Mart van de Ven&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project aims to establish relations between the packages of cereal and their nutrition values.&lt;br&gt;The majority of the content here would be repeated in PyCON Hong Kong 2015, with important additions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicate and Visualize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Words-of-Suuport&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Words-of-Suuport&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Words of Suuport&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Words of Suuport&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Donal Ellis, Enterprise Support Engineer with GitHub, talked about support, focusing on writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slides is available here:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/donal/hkcodeconf/blob/master/words_of_support.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/donal/hkcodeconf/blob/master/words_of_support.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write Well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rewrite at least once&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t use big words, technical jargons, cliche, et cetera.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read it aloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t use emoji.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t apologize unless we mean it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If English is your second language, write straightforward. Don’t overwrite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151112-Hong-Kong-Code-Conf-2015/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>哪國大學裏女生比例最高？聯合國超全數據集告訴你</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151106-gender-parity-in-education-and-un-mdg/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151106-gender-parity-in-education-and-un-mdg/</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 08:24:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;你上學時，女同學多還是男同學多？在貧窮的國家，女孩往往缺少平等的受教育機會。但經濟也許並非唯一因素。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們選取了 4 個國家，分别繪製 1990 年以来入學性別比例的折线圖。縱軸表示女學生與男學生的人數之比，如果數值小於 1.0 ，則代表女學生少於男學生。藍色、綠色、紅色折線分別指初等、中等、高等教育。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151106-gender-parity-in-education-and-un-mdg/4-country-gender.png&quot; alt=&quot;猜猜這 4 張圖分別是中國、美國、日本、印度之中的哪個國家？&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;猜猜這 4 張圖分別是&lt;strong&gt;中國、美國、日本、印度&lt;/strong&gt;之中的哪個國家？&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;你上學時，女同學多還是男同學多？在貧窮的國家，女孩往往缺少平等的受教育機會。但經濟也許並非唯一因素。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們選取了 4 個國家，分别繪製 1990 年以来入學性別比例的折线圖。縱軸表示女學生與男學生的人數之比，如果數值小於 1.0 ，則代表女學生少於男學生。藍色、綠色、紅色折線分別指初等、中等、高等教育。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151106-gender-parity-in-education-and-un-mdg/4-country-gender.png&quot; alt=&quot;猜猜這 4 張圖分別是中國、美國、日本、印度之中的哪個國家？&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;猜猜這 4 張圖分別是&lt;strong&gt;中國、美國、日本、印度&lt;/strong&gt;之中的哪個國家？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;圖 A：女學生比例低，但增長迅速。&lt;br&gt;圖 B：女學生比例呈增長趨勢，其中初等、中等教育的性別比例已經在 2005 年前後穩定在 1:1 的水平。高等教育中女學生比例增長迅速。&lt;br&gt;圖 C：初等和中等教育的性別比例在 1990 年之前已经達到均衡。高校女生比例經過了二十年的增長，仍然低於男生。&lt;br&gt;圖 D：初等和中等教育的情況與圖 C 一樣都是 1:1，高校女生比例高得驚人。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;正確答案是：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;圖 A：印度。&lt;br&gt;圖 B：中國。&lt;br&gt;圖 C：日本。&lt;br&gt;圖 D：美國。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相信大家憑藉對中國、美國、日本、印度這 4 個國家的經濟和文化的基本了解就能猜出大半。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;女學生和男學生的比例，是&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.un.org/zh/millenniumgoals/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;聯合國八項千年發展目標&lt;/a&gt;之一的「促進兩性平等並賦予婦女權力」之中一個關鍵指標。2015 年是聯合國千年發展目標的預定完成年份，那麼現在進度如何呢？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;聯合國自己也想知道，所以把所有指標的數據公開了出來供社會公衆分析，裏面包含了各國歷年來在所有指標上的表現。入學性別比例只是冰山一角，經濟發展、環境保護、健康衛生等社會熱點議題都在這個數據集中對應着豐富的材料。如果你愛好數據分析，一定能從這個數據集中掘出寶藏。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;更詳細的說明請見&lt;a href=&quot;http://mdgs.un.org/unsd/mdg/Data.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;聯合國對此數據集的介紹&lt;/a&gt;。如果你已迫不及待要拿整個數據集，&lt;a href=&quot;https://unite.un.org/ideas/sites/unite.un.org.ideas/files/public/MdgDatabase_2015WSD_DataVizChallenge.zip&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;就直接點擊這裏下載聯合國官方數據集壓縮包吧&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151106-gender-parity-in-education-and-un-mdg/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initium Lab at BarCamp Hong Kong 2015</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 02:16:16 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;On 17 October 2015, &lt;a href=&quot;http://barcamp.hk/&quot;&gt;Barcamp 2015&lt;/a&gt; was held in Hong Kong and Initium Lab presented 3 sections of sharing, with an additional panel discussion planned onsite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our topics on the topic board. After the sessions, the audience can stick red stickers on the topic to show appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/barcamp-hk-initiumlab-topics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initium Lab prepared 3 talks for Barcamp Hong Kong 2015: on JavaScript, QRCode, and Hong Kong District Council Data&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;On 17 October 2015, &lt;a href=&quot;http://barcamp.hk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Barcamp 2015&lt;/a&gt; was held in Hong Kong and Initium Lab presented 3 sections of sharing, with an additional panel discussion planned onsite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our topics on the topic board. After the sessions, the audience can stick red stickers on the topic to show appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/barcamp-hk-initiumlab-topics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initium Lab prepared 3 talks for Barcamp Hong Kong 2015: on JavaScript, QRCode, and Hong Kong District Council Data&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Learn-JavaScript-like-a-Natural-Language&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Learn-JavaScript-like-a-Natural-Language&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Learn JavaScript like a Natural Language&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Learn JavaScript like a Natural Language&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Andy Shu, News Engineer with Initium Lab, shared his experience of migrating skills in Natural Language Acquisition to accelerate learning programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/andy-barcamp-hk-javascript.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Andy Shu talking about Learning JavaScript&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy outlined 6 tactics of natural language learning applicable to learning programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is to get to the “minimallly viable proficiency” as soon as possible, at which point the language becomes useful to the learner. After that point, learning turns self-sustainable as learning directly brings benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is spaced repetition, which basically says you should review materials often in small chuncks, rather than trying to memorize everything in one shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third is “comprehensible input + 1”, meaning the learners should try to read materials slightly above their level, rather than dwelling in their comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth is using existing mental models to understand unfamiliar concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fifth is shadow writing, which refers to the exercises of writing code and compare it with exemplary code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sixth is learning with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slides with details about the learning strategies are available here:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1JXdyXiFjXKw5w4zkbtVUDXG0CFhYlLCkaGMghktvjgg/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1JXdyXiFjXKw5w4zkbtVUDXG0CFhYlLCkaGMghktvjgg/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Cold-Knowledge-on-QRCode&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Cold-Knowledge-on-QRCode&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Cold Knowledge on QRCode&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Cold Knowledge on QRCode&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hu Pili talked about the less known side of QR Code, for example, QRCode can be hacked and direct to another URL if someone filling originally blank cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also demonstrated how to make functional QRCodes with image patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/hupili-barcamp-hk-qrcode-avatar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QRCode looking like profile pictures&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/hupili-barcamp-hk-qrcode-dressedup-audience.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;An audience dressed up in traditional Chinese attire taking photo of the QRCode demonstrated by Hu Pili&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slides are available at:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Pb4JVbmOpSHdZdiHEfaXJCo0YCyTKC7iEDeD8odD8k4/pub?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Pb4JVbmOpSHdZdiHEfaXJCo0YCyTKC7iEDeD8odD8k4/pub?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Panel-Talk-Internet-Media-Winter-is-Coming&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Panel-Talk-Internet-Media-Winter-is-Coming&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Panel Talk: Internet Media - Winter is Coming?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Panel Talk: Internet Media - Winter is Coming?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fully in the spirit of Barcamp, Andy met a few fellow practitioners in the Internet-based Media and decided during the conference to hold a panel talk about Internet Media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kris Cheng of Hong Kong Free Press, Franky Chu of InMedia, and Andy shared each others’ experience and vision, majorly about the the sustainablity of serious Journalism in an era flooded with free information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/andy-barcamp-hk-media-panel-talk.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Kris, Franky, and Andy sharing experiences&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Live-Data-Mining-Hong-Kong-District-Council&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Live-Data-Mining-Hong-Kong-District-Council&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Live Data Mining: Hong Kong District Council&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Live Data Mining: Hong Kong District Council&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chao Tianyi, Researcher of Initium Lab, Hu Pili and Andy held a live data mining section demonstrating the potential use of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/initiummedia/hk_district_council_election&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Hong Kong District Council Election data&lt;/a&gt;, as well as use of data processing tools such as Google Spreadsheet, Fusion Table, and Refine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience supplied questions about the elections and we answer them with the data in hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/chao-andy-hupili-barcamp-hk-live-datamining-mapmaking.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Chao Tianyi, Hu Pili, and Andy working on the dataset to answer questions&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also participated talks by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;How-could-IT-Help-to-Democratize-Christianity&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#How-could-IT-Help-to-Democratize-Christianity&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;How could IT Help to Democratize Christianity&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How could IT Help to Democratize Christianity&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frankie Ng from Ekklesia Hong Kong starts a conversion with other participants about democratizing the Christian Chuches in Hong Kong. He highlights the political potential of the 350 thousand Christians in Hong Kong, many of whom can vote for electors for the Election Committee for the Chief Executive of Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participants contributed ideas that Hong Kong Christians should have a new platform to discuss politics. Another participant shared his experience promoting Open Source in Hong Kong, pointing out that it is usually not the (techincal) platform that is missing, rather, it is that we are often rushed to achieve something, while communication is inadequate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;PHP-is-the-Best-Language&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#PHP-is-the-Best-Language&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;PHP is the Best Language&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;PHP is the Best Language&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A supporter of PHP, whose name is beyond our recollection, talked about the benefits of PHP and the ecosystem and toolchain.&lt;br&gt;He first refuted the criticism that “PHP is old” by noting that JavaScript is also old. (Editors’ note: Both PHP and JavaScript appeared in 1995.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then introduced to the audience PHP7, which is twice as fast as the previous PHP in many cases. A few tools were mentioned:&lt;br&gt;Silex, which is like express;&lt;br&gt;Laravel, which is like Rails;&lt;br&gt;ReactPHP, event-driven &amp;amp; non-blocking I/O just like Node.js;&lt;br&gt;Symfony, a component library and a framework,;&lt;br&gt;composer, packagist, both package managers;&lt;br&gt;PHPUnit, a testing framework;&lt;br&gt;Behat for BDD; and&lt;br&gt;Blackfire for profiling.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151105-barcamp-hk-2015/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jackathon #5 -- Read a journalism book in 8 hours</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2015 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;Still remember the “read-one-book-in-eight-hours” activity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weeks ago, in &lt;a href=&quot;http://initiumlab.com/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/&quot;&gt;Jackathon #3&lt;/a&gt; , we turned our lab as a reading club , and had a fruitful day reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html/&quot;&gt;Data Science books&lt;/a&gt;. This time, the theme was to read something journalistic. 11 participants were required to finish reading one or two books in 8 hours, and share their findings or insights in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/Discussion.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Discussion&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Still remember the “read-one-book-in-eight-hours” activity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weeks ago, in &lt;a href=&quot;http://initiumlab.com/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/&quot;&gt;Jackathon #3&lt;/a&gt; , we turned our lab as a reading club , and had a fruitful day reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Data Science books&lt;/a&gt;. This time, the theme was to read something journalistic. 11 participants were required to finish reading one or two books in 8 hours, and share their findings or insights in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/Discussion.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Discussion&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Andy’s-introduction-Which-journalism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Andy’s-introduction-Which-journalism&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Andy’s introduction: Which journalism?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Andy’s introduction: Which journalism?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Andy Shu introduced the books by illustrating an broadstroke outline of the intellectual disciplines that eventually lead to Journalism. He started with medieval universities, which usually house four “departments”: Arts, Medicine, Law, and Theology. The Arts department taught Trivium, i.e. Latin Grammar, Rhetorics, and Logic. It also taught Philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From “Traditional Philosophy”, that of Socrates and Aristotle, stemmed “Natural Philosophy”, the empirical study of the this world. Natural Philosophy gave birth to Science. Science developed and branched into three sub-fields: natural sciences, cognitive sciences, and social sciences. Natural sciences, such as Physics and Chemistry, study the physical world. Cognitive sciences and social sciences both study humans, the difference being cognitive sciences study the internal state of individual humans while social sciences focus on the interaction between humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalism roughly inherit from the Trivium tradition, paying keen attention to the power of words. Yet Journalism is also a trade. Journalism has a strong feeling of tradition and emphasize on the practitioners’ conscience and conduct. In this aspect, Journalism is similar to the craft of Law and Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy explained that the book list contains several scientific books because Journalism could learn a lot from the Science tradition - be it Cognitive Psychology, which studies human thinking and biases, or Probability Theory, which studies uncertainty. Click here to see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TBDLthpxy4S_gaHcJB63RzQCcOlOwmceh-UBigx76yg/edit#heading=h.5kxx2s6j5imj&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;book list&lt;/a&gt; made by Andy and Tianyi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/Book-Stack.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Book Stack&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Journalism-Practice&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Journalism-Practice&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Journalism Practice&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Journalism Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;Data-Journalism-Handbook&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Data-Journalism-Handbook&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Data Journalism Handbook&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Data Journalism Handbook&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yan Rong, a student majoring in mass communication, skimmed the Data Journalism Handbook and recommended it to beginners. The book introduced the workflow of doing data driven news by sharing many real-life cases in newsroom. Yan found that, for data journalists, the main task was to help audience understand data with cautious interpretation. Besides, she shared a case she found inspiring in the book. After the Fukushima nuclear disaster, Zeit Online, a German online media, simulated the situation when similar nuclear contamination happened in Germany, and made a map showing how many people would have to be evacuated then. “This project stood out, for it told a concrete data story and successfully engaged audience into a piece of news seemingly had no relation with them”, said Yan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;中國數據新聞工作坊培訓手冊&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#中國數據新聞工作坊培訓手冊&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;中國數據新聞工作坊培訓手冊&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;中國數據新聞工作坊培訓手冊&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kate Liu, UX assistant with Initium Lab, read the book 中國數據新聞工作坊培訓手冊. She found the book was quite helpful for freshmen. The book is a compilation of a training workshop in mainland China which taught the whole flow of data journalism, including searching and getting data from different portals, using Excel and Open Refine to clean and analyze data, and visualizing data with AI and code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Verification-handbook-for-investigative-reporting&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Verification-handbook-for-investigative-reporting&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Verification handbook for investigative reporting&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Verification handbook for investigative reporting&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Verification handbook for investigative reporting tells readers how to get accurate information from sources of different credibilities. Tianyi picked this book and made a list of all tools mentioned in the book. She thought the skills applied to verifying user-generated contents are the highlight part. In a case, to verify whether a new war crime occurred in Nigeria, journalists examined a user-generated video frame by frame, extracting specifications of the road as well as details related to people, compare them with satellite images to check location. Additionally, they examined metadata in photos from different sources with EXif reader and did crosscheck. They even inverted picture color to see ID number printed on rifle in one frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Reading books](/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/Reading-Books.jpeg)
 --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Thinking-Pattern&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Thinking-Pattern&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Thinking Pattern&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Thinking Pattern&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;Signal-and-Noise&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Signal-and-Noise&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Signal and Noise&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Signal and Noise&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sally Chong, a video journalist with rich experience, chose the book The Signal and Noise by Nate Silver, a statistician as well as founder of the data journalism blog &lt;a href=&quot;http://fivethirtyeight.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;FiveThirtyEight&lt;/a&gt;. The book tries to analyze how people predict future based on data about the past. She introduced three thinking patterns that would lead to flawed predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first error is out-of-sample, which happens when you make deduction from a sample that doesn’t contain relevant cases, hence, out-of-sample. One example is a drunk driver think he won’t have an accident, because he never had any accident driving sober.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second mistake is overfitting, which occurs when your solution is only applied to the available data in specific, rather than all possible data in general; in other words, you try too hard to fit your theory to the current data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third issue to take note of is false-positive. This concept is better illustrated with an example. Let’s say 1000 people went for a cancer check, and some people are diagnosed as cancer carrier. Let’s assume the cancer check has a possibility of 90% to be correct. The question is, among these people being diagnosed with cancer, how many actually have cancer? Hint: it’s not 90% of them. Second hint: we don’t know yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To know the exact number of people with cancer, we need to know how many of the 1000 people are cancer carriers to begin with. Let’s say 50 of them do. So we start with 50 ill and 950 healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cancer check is 90% correct. That means 950 &lt;em&gt; 90% = 855 healthy people are correctly diagnosed as healthy; 950 &lt;/em&gt; 10% = 95 healthy people are incorrectly labelled as ill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, 50 &lt;em&gt; 90% = 45 ill people are correctly diagnosed, while 50 &lt;/em&gt; 10% = 5 ill people are wrongly diagnosed as healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in total, 95 + 45 = 140 people are diagnosed by the medical check to have cancer; yet, only 45 (32%) of them actually do, not 90%. The reason it’s not 90% is the cancer check marked a lot of healthy people as ill, due to the sheer number of healthy people. Those wrongly labelled people, called false-positive, “diluted” the final outcome. So, when we see a “positive” result, we need to think about how many of the positive results are actually positive and how many are false-positives. This effect is especially significant in rare events, such as having cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Thinking-fast-and-slow&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Thinking-fast-and-slow&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Thinking, fast and slow&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Thinking, fast and slow&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thinking, fast and slow is another book about human thinking pattern. Nancy Hu found it filled with experiments and real-life examples. The book mainly targets to explore how rational people are when making decisions. The author found out that two totally different systems in human brain are driving the way we think. System 1 is based on intuition, emotions and previous experiences. It reacts fast and unconsciously, which is more like the default mode. Meanwhile, System 2 engages complex brain activity (like logical thinking) while working, but it only activates when System 1 gets stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;A-Tradecraft-Primer-Structured-Analytic-Techniques-for-Improving-Intelligence-Analysis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#A-Tradecraft-Primer-Structured-Analytic-Techniques-for-Improving-Intelligence-Analysis&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;A Tradecraft Primer: Structured Analytic Techniques for Improving Intelligence Analysis&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A Tradecraft Primer: Structured Analytic Techniques for Improving Intelligence Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pili Hu, data scientist with Initium Lab, chose A Tradecraft Primer: Structured Analytic Techniques for Improving Intelligence Analysis. “The book lists 12 practical techniques to improve structured analytics, with a core goal to train people think as rationally as machine”, Pili introduced. He made an analytic form for the 12 techniques, and found the “Analysis of Competing Hypotheses” the most hardcore one. The technique requires people to have more hypothesis and unbiased sample collection in decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/Pili-Hu-Presenting.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Pili Hu is presenting&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Writing&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Writing&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Writing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;On-Writing-Well&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#On-Writing-Well&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;On Writing Well&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;On Writing Well&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;First published in 1976, On Writing Well is a classic guide for writing news. Natalie Lung, majoring both in journalism and computer science, picked this book. The book can be divided into four parts: principles of good writing, methods to polish up, guide for writing different forms and mind-setting tips. The author offered a bunch of practical tips, for example, he held that science and technology news should not be a story simply about science but a story about people doing science. Besides reporters, the book is also good for people who have interests in writing or blogging. As the author encourages, “you write for yourself”, just write the things that attracts you and familiar to you, and anyone could become a good writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Sense-of-Style&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Sense-of-Style&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Sense of Style&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Sense of Style&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Sense of Style is a relatively recent writing style guidebook which was published in 2014. “I think the book is responding to old school journalism textbooks like the Elements of Style (1920), and On Writing Well (1976) just shared by Natalie as well. The author pointed out a lot of new values which are contrary to tradition but well functioning in contemporary society”, said Guo Yanan, a social science major student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Textbooks used to teach people strictly follow grammar rules, but The Sense of Style held a view that only a minority group of people still care that much. Nowadays young people are making and accepting new language conventions. In addition, the author encouraged writers to use a diverse and “unusual” vocabulary, especially the words would echo it in their sound and articulation. As for the “writing for yourself” theory, the book shares a quite different view with On Writing Well. “Don’t confuse an anecdote or a personal experience with the state of the world”, as the author put, suggesting trend stories are of more significance than stories about personal experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/Yanan-Presenting.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yanan is presenting&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;History&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#History&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;History&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;News-People-Serving-the-Country&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#News-People-Serving-the-Country&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;News People Serving the Country&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;News People Serving the Country&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Victoria Jin, Initium Lab’s interactive designer read this one. This book consists of 15 papers. The papers give an account of Chinese news people’s awkward situation during the period of Republic of China. Some main discussions are highlighted in the book: the development of public sphere,  the contradiction of liberalism, the standards of good news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The public sphere is an area where individuals get together to freely discuss and identify social problems. Qing yi (清議) is regarded as China’s earliest public sphere. However, comparing to western world, public opinion in Chinese society lacked consensus, rationality and tolerance due to weak middle class and absent civic consciousness, and also because of the breaking down of family as an institution and its incapability as a buffer area between public sphere and individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of newspaper is built on the philosopher of liberalism, which also faces an embarrassing situation in China. For news people, national independence and modernization are two contradictory but equally significant objectives, that’s why liberalism get criticisms from both left and right parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A missing squire group also makes the scholars to play an important role in history. Some important names are mentioned in the book: Hu Shi realized that media should be impartial, She Chengwo promoted the civilization of media, Chen Leng insisted that newspaper should be professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are strict standards to evaluate the quality of news at that time. Firstly, newspaper should be accurate with researches, allusions and stereotyped expressions. Secondly, a good story should be fulfilled with analysis and interpretation so as to connect fragmentary incidents in history as a whole. Finally, newspaper materials should be consistency in logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Reading-Methods&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Reading-Methods&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Reading Methods&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Reading Methods&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;How-to-read-a-book-Chinese-version&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#How-to-read-a-book-Chinese-version&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;How to read a book? (Chinese version)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How to read a book? (Chinese version)&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;How to Read a Book introduces a structural way of reading. According to this book, reading is divided into four levels - elementary reading, inspectional reading, analytical reading, and syntopical reading. The latter two are the focus of this book. In Frank Lin’s opinion, this book is a ‘must read’ for inexperienced readers since it builds your ‘reading sense’ from the ground up, while experience readers may find it too detailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;What-is-Jackathon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#What-is-Jackathon&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;What is Jackathon?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What is Jackathon?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jackathon is short for “Journalism-Hackathon”. At Initium Lab, we do data journalism, try digital storytelling and push limits of the news industry with technology. We organize regular Jackathons to advance our knowledge and skills in both journalism and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edited by Chao Tianyi&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151025-jackathon-no-5/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infographic for the Blind: We Tried 3D Printing That Almost Worked</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151015-3d-infographic-user-testing/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151015-3d-infographic-user-testing/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2015 08:26:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        We tested a 3D-printed LegcoMatrix infographic with the first blind user Chong Chan Yau, president of Hong Kong Blind Union. The solution almost worked and we got valuable advices from him on how to further polish the work.
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Based on vote records of 2921 motions of current Hong Kong Legislative Council meetings, Initium Lab analyzed the voting patterns of 70 legislators in &lt;a href=&quot;http://initiumlab.com/#legco&quot;&gt;Legco Matrix&lt;/a&gt; project. For visualization, we made a heat map of 70 rows by 70 columns, with the brightness of each cell representing supportiveness from one voter towards one motion mover (in terms of the percentage of supporting votes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heat map might be helpful for many who wanted to have insights into Hong Kong politics, but definitely not for the blind. Actually, nowadays, only a few of the fancy digital news products have really taken visually-challenged people into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet in Initium Lab, we do care about news accessibility. With the help from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.makeblock.cc/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;MakeBlock&lt;/a&gt; engineers, we &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hupili/heatmap2stl&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;turned the heat map into 3D model&lt;/a&gt; and managed producing an array of touchable blocks using 3D printing technology. Each cell in the heat map was printed as a small pillar, and the height of pillars represented strength of support. By doing so, we hoped we could introduce the beauty of data to the visually impaired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 2nd 2015, for the first time, we tested this 3D-printed infographic with a blind user – Chong Chan Yau, president of Hong Kong Blind Union as well as a politically active celebrity in Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-3d-infographic-user-testing/introducing-heatmap.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;We introduced the meaning of the heat map to Mr. Chong&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With our explanation and assistance, Mr. Chong managed to roughly understand the infographic’s idea in about ten minutes, yet he found it greatly difficult to read specific blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Chong said one would easily get lost when navigating with finger, because the pillars were too small and too densely arranged. He suggested that we put marks on each pillar showing the value it represents, say, one marked 80% on the top and the other 40%. With these marks, blind users could feel the quantitative differences between the pillars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Braille was another problem. Mr. Chong thought we put those small braille characters together in a vague way, for we did not notice that the space between two braille characters and the space between two columns inside one character were different . Meanwhile, he emphasized that we should be cautious about block size and gap of braille characters by following standards. He also reminded us to note visually-challenged people’s reading direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-3d-infographic-user-testing/explaining-braille-character.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Mr. Chong explaining braille characters&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these practical and considerate suggestions, Mr. Chong Chan Yau encouraged us to keep experimenting physical infographics and turn the cool idea into a real solution stack for the blind. He highlighted the novelty of our 3D infographic, remarking that he had never seen such approach to presenting data before.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151015-3d-infographic-user-testing/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>在Facebook找新聞線索？FB Signal搶鮮試用</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2015 03:28:04 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;2015年9月17日，Facebook 推出 Signal，專為新聞家設計，用來在 Facebook 和 Instagram 上發掘新聞線索。12個小時之前，我們收到了Signal試用權限，下面為大家介紹我們試用Signal的經驗。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signal 目前功能可以分為四類：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;探索（發現還不知道的的線索）；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;搜索（調研、比較已知的關鍵字）；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;收納（收納相關的話題和信息）；和&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;發佈（分享調研成果）。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;2015年9月17日，Facebook 推出 Signal，專為新聞家設計，用來在 Facebook 和 Instagram 上發掘新聞線索。12個小時之前，我們收到了Signal試用權限，下面為大家介紹我們試用Signal的經驗。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signal 目前功能可以分為四類：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;探索（發現還不知道的的線索）；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;搜索（調研、比較已知的關鍵字）；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;收納（收納相關的話題和信息）；和&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;發佈（分享調研成果）。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;探索&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#探索&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;探索&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;探索&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;探索功能分兩部分：一個是「Trending」，顯示熱點事件；一個是「Leaderboards」，顯示熱點人物。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trending是這樣子的：&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/trends-interface.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，Trending功能的界面&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;除了提供Facebook用自家算法判斷的熱點消息，還有&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crowdtangle.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;CrowdTangle&lt;/a&gt;和&lt;a href=&quot;https://storyful.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Storyful&lt;/a&gt;各自追蹤的熱點。（CrowdTangle和Storyful提供社交媒體追蹤、內容發掘服務。）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trending講事，Leaderboards則講人，顯示每一天最多人談論的人物排行。&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/leaderboards-interface.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，Leaderboard的界面&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;點擊事件或人名，還可以集中看關於這個話題的討論。&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/leaderboard-details.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，Leaderboard的個人詳細資料界面&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;搜索&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#搜索&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;搜索&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;搜索&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Signal的搜索功能乏善可陳。&lt;br&gt;主要搜索功能是關鍵詞討論量比較：&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/comparison-interface.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，關鍵詞討論量地理分佈&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/comparison-interface-by-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，關鍵詞討論量時間變化&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;還有Facebook和Instagram的搜索，但是搜索效果並不出彩，可能還不如Facebook和Instagram的站內搜索。&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/facebook-search-interface.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，Facebook搜索界面&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/instagram-search-interface.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，Instagram搜索界面&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;收納&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#收納&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;收納&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;收納&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Signal提供消息收納功能，可以建立文件夾（Collection），收藏一組相關的信息。目前，消息、數據和搜索結果只能分開存檔，不能放到一起。&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/collection-adding.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，添加文章到Collection&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/collection-interface.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal，Collection界面&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;發佈&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#發佈&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;發佈&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;發佈&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Signal的發佈功能主要針對之前在收納中建立的文件夾，有兩種發佈方式，內置方式和導出JSON。&lt;br&gt;內置的發佈功能要求文件夾至少有26篇文章才能發佈，但是似乎有bug，我們創建的有30篇文章的文件夾也顯示發佈不了，於是我們也無法測試了。&lt;br&gt;文件夾內容也可以導出JSON，只要再寫個前端，就可以用自己喜歡的方式顯示收藏夾了。&lt;br&gt;具體的API寫得不太清楚，其實是要POST一個JSON過去，具體格式像這樣：&lt;br&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight json&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;customerId&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;YOUR_CUSTOMER_ID_FROM_FACEBOOK&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;$in&lt;/span&gt;&quot;:&lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;[&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;text&quot;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;image&quot;&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;source&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;$in&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;[&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;facebook.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;instagram.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;limit&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;就會得到類似這樣的反饋：&lt;br&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight json&quot;&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;26&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;27&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;28&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;29&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;31&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;33&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;34&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;35&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;36&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;37&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;38&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;39&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;entries&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    &amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;45623437315_10154528665262316&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;source&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;facebook.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;image&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;Stars and Stripes&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;icon&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;https://scontent.xx.fbcdn.net/hprofile-xpf1/v/t1.0-1/p50x50/222454_10150338647532316_7301889_n.jpg?oh=154900aa9099bcf05c61426fc607ce8d&amp;amp;oe=568A9741&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;published&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1444884240000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;Thursday’s front page:\n\n• PHOTOS | Afghan aircraft form lifeline to besieged cities: www.stripes.com/1.373263\n\n• Navy considering expanding paternity leave, top Navy officer says: www.stripes.com/1.373178\n\n• Carter: US will sail near Spratly Islands any time it wants: http://www.stripes.com/1.373151\n\n• Clinton, Sanders dominate Democrats&#39; 1st go on the debate stage: www.stripes.com/1.373183&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;likes&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;31&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;link&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;https://www.facebook.com/45623437315/posts/10154528665262316&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;ssMetaData&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;facebookId&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;45623437315_10154528665262316&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;images&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;          &amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;            &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;source&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;https://scontent.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xtp1/v/t1.0-9/s720x720/12111948_10154528665262316_5154848867614938223_n.jpg?oh=11c051355d4a0da54a31fe13989d222d&amp;amp;oe=56C95F7D&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;            &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;549&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;            &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;720&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        ]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;ssFacebookPostId&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;45623437315_10154528665262316&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;ssFbData&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;          &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;Stars and Stripes&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;          &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;45623437315&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;&quot;Timeline Photos&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;_feedItem&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;literal&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;moderationFlags&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;        &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;stageOneModeration&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;literal&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  ]&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;olderThan&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;    &quot;&lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;accounts_server&lt;/span&gt;&quot;: &lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1444833155000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;line&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;結語&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#結語&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;結語&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;結語&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;目前 Facebook Signal 的核心競爭力在於探索熱點事件——搜索功能還不成熟；收藏和發佈功能似乎有潛力，但應用場景並不清晰。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;無論如何，Facebook 涉足新聞業野心勃勃，Signal 想必也會繼續演進，值得持續關注。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;申請試用Facebook Signal，請在此填表：&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/help/contact/1584814605121989&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/help/contact/1584814605121989&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;花絮&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#花絮&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;花絮&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;花絮&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Signal 是用 Google 家的 Angular 框架搭建的，而沒有用 Facebook 自己的 React。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/signal-angular.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facebook Signal源代碼裏有Angular的痕跡&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;(Signal 用的是 Angular 1.2.28，是個舊版本，發佈了快一年了。)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;這是個什麼概念呢？就好像法拉利造了個新車，外面看上去是法拉利，開起來也像法拉利，卻用了是隔壁寶馬五年前造的引擎……&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;（當然，互聯網互相借用技術也是司空見慣的事，比如 Google Chrome 的一開始的渲染引擎用的是 Apple 給 Safari 做的 WebKit。那麼究竟爲什麼 Signal 這麼選？我們也不知道，如果讀者您知道，請留言告訴我們。）&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151015-Facebook-Signal-Review/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>一張圖讀懂喬布斯數據化妝術</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 07:56:40 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        一組平平無奇的銷量數據，經過喬布斯一番可視化，一下就顯得前途無量。究竟他是怎麼做到的？我們閱讀、製作數據可視化，又應該對哪些手法多加留意？
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;喬布斯是個頂級的企業家，也是頂級的營銷家，玩起數據可視化來，也是便宜佔盡，毫不手軟。&lt;br&gt;我們選用喬布斯在2006年 Macworld 上的一張棒圖，拆解他的數據化妝術。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2006年 Macworld 上，喬布斯向觀衆展示蘋果 Mac 產品在2005年四個季度的銷量：&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/mac-sales-2005-macword.png&quot; alt=&quot;喬布斯展示蘋果產品銷量逐年遞增&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;增長勢頭很厲害啊，不過，好像有什麼不對？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;這四個棒的基線並不是零，而是1000，所以變化似乎非常大。那麼，我們用同樣一組數據，只是將基線換成0，會如何？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/mac-sales-2005-base0.png&quot; alt=&quot;喬布斯展示蘋果產品銷量逐年遞增，改爲以0爲基礎&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;馬上縮水了一圈啊……&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/more-gelivable.png&quot; alt=&quot;再給力一點行不行啊，老師&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;然後，我們留意到這個棒圖是 3D 的，應用透視關係，近的會變大，顯得增長勢頭很強。於是，我們再將這個圖還原成 2D 的……&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/mac-sales-2005-2d.png&quot; alt=&quot;喬布斯展示蘋果產品銷量逐年遞增，轉爲二維版本&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;好了，拆到這裏，其實就差不多還原到這個數據圖樸素的狀態了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/more-gelivable.png&quot; alt=&quot;再給力一點行不行啊，老師&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;如果比爾蓋茨來給喬布斯做設計……&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#如果比爾蓋茨來給喬布斯做設計……&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;如果比爾蓋茨來給喬布斯做設計……&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;如果比爾蓋茨來給喬布斯做設計……&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;當然，我們是不會就此罷休的。下面，我們假裝自己是喬布斯的老對頭比爾蓋茨，想方設法破壞老喬的演講。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;喬布斯想強調季度之間的變化，自然用棒圖，讓兩季之間有明顯的高低差別。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們想抹平差別，則可以用線圖，給兩季度之間的變化添加過渡。而且，沒有了棒圖的棒爲主體，整個圖空空如也，更突出銷量薄弱。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/mac-sales-2005-line.png&quot; alt=&quot;喬布斯展示蘋果產品銷量逐年遞增，轉爲線圖&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/more-gelivable.png&quot; alt=&quot;再給力一點行不行啊，老師&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;剛纔是玩圖像本身，我們現在來調圖像的外框比例。正方型改成長方形，再次削弱高低差別。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/mac-sales-2005-flatline.png&quot; alt=&quot;喬布斯展示蘋果產品銷量逐年遞增，正方形邊框轉爲長方形&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/more-gelivable.png&quot; alt=&quot;再給力一點行不行啊，老師&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所謂水能載舟，亦能覆舟，喬布斯用3D來強調增長，蓋茨也可以用 3D 來削弱增長，甚至讓視覺效果違背實際趨勢。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;下面這個圖，用的還是同一組數據，但是精心調校視角和透視關係——雖然 Mac 銷量每年在增加，從視覺上看，倒似乎先增後減。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/mac-sales-2005-3darea.png&quot; alt=&quot;喬布斯展示蘋果產品銷量逐年遞增，3D版本&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們再回顧喬布斯本人選擇的可視化，可以看到，即使用完全相同數據，也能做出傾向完全相反的可視化：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/mac-sales-2005-macword.png&quot; alt=&quot;喬布斯展示蘋果產品銷量逐年遞增&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;總結&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#總結&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;總結&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;總結&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;以下手法會強調數據變化：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;加入3D透視，放大最近的數據圖像；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;提升基線，除去棒圖不變的部分，突出變化的部分；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;用高寬接近的圖像外框比例。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相反，以下手法會削弱數據變化：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;加入3D透視，縮小最近的數據圖像；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;用寬而扁的圖像外框比例。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;以數據新聞而言，使用3D透視需要非常謹慎，因爲一旦引入3D透視，你就可以扭曲原數據的趨勢，即使數據一直增長，也可以可視化爲下跌。&lt;br&gt;基線一般用0爲宜，但有時候卻又確實需要升高，否則幾乎看不到變化。這個需要新聞人自行判斷，並明確標註。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;至於高寬比，有各平臺適配需要考慮，寬圖多適合桌面，方形、窄高的圖則適合手機。編輯須留意外框比例這對可視化語義的影響。&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151012-visualization-via-jobs/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>數據新聞人，今夜我們談色</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 03:59:20 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;做數據可視化，繞不開的設計元素是「色」——顏色的色。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;顏色是什麼？有人說，光有「三原色」，世間一切顏色，皆是這三原色組合而成。其實，光就是光，就是電磁波，只有波長、強弱之分。所謂顏色，是生物體神經系統決定的歸類，並不是光本身的特性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;其實我們都是色盲&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#其實我們都是色盲&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;其實我們都是色盲&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;其實我們都是色盲&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;大多數人有三種視覺細胞，分別對紅、綠、藍最爲敏感，對這些人而言，顏色就有三原色。大約8%的男性很難辨別紅綠：對他們來說，顏色只有二原色，一個是黃色（紅、綠都像黃色），一個是藍色。每三萬人之中，還有一個是單色視覺，對他們來說，只有亮暗之別。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大多數哺乳動物都是二色視覺，比如老虎獅子。人類有三色視覺，比他們強，不過跟昆蟲、爬行類相比，又遠遠不如。很多昆蟲都是四色視覺。四色視覺是什麼意思？就是它們眼中比我們多一種感光細胞，對人類來說相似的顏色（比方說深黃和淺黃），對蝴蝶來說是截然不同的顏色。&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;做數據可視化，繞不開的設計元素是「色」——顏色的色。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;顏色是什麼？有人說，光有「三原色」，世間一切顏色，皆是這三原色組合而成。其實，光就是光，就是電磁波，只有波長、強弱之分。所謂顏色，是生物體神經系統決定的歸類，並不是光本身的特性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;其實我們都是色盲&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#其實我們都是色盲&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;其實我們都是色盲&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;其實我們都是色盲&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;大多數人有三種視覺細胞，分別對紅、綠、藍最爲敏感，對這些人而言，顏色就有三原色。大約8%的男性很難辨別紅綠：對他們來說，顏色只有二原色，一個是黃色（紅、綠都像黃色），一個是藍色。每三萬人之中，還有一個是單色視覺，對他們來說，只有亮暗之別。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大多數哺乳動物都是二色視覺，比如老虎獅子。人類有三色視覺，比他們強，不過跟昆蟲、爬行類相比，又遠遠不如。很多昆蟲都是四色視覺。四色視覺是什麼意思？就是它們眼中比我們多一種感光細胞，對人類來說相似的顏色（比方說深黃和淺黃），對蝴蝶來說是截然不同的顏色。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/colour-blindness-is-relative.png&quot; alt=&quot;色盲是相對的&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;四色視覺，對大多數人來說只能靠想像了，不過，還有更強的，那就是皮皮蝦（瀨尿蝦）。多數人類有3種色覺細胞，昆蟲有4種，少數蝴蝶有5種，而皮皮蝦有16種。是的，你沒看錯，16種。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/mantis-colour-vision.png&quot; alt=&quot;皮皮蝦能看到很多顏色&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;能看見一億種顏色的人&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#能看見一億種顏色的人&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;能看見一億種顏色的人&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;能看見一億種顏色的人&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;前面說，四色視覺，對大多數人來說只能靠想像了。這樣說是因爲，有極個別人天生有四色視覺。比如澳大利亞藝術家 Concetta Antico 。三色視覺的人能分辨幾百萬種顏色。她能分辨一億種。經過研究，她的第四種「原色」是介於紅色和黃色之間的顏色。換句話說，對大多數人來說，紅色、橙色、黃色比較相似，對她來說，則是截然不同。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antico的畫作與景物照片的對比：&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/antico-tree-painting-and-reality.png&quot; alt=&quot;Antico的畫作與景物照片的對比&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;(圖片來自BBC和畫作者本人：&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20140905-the-women-with-super-human-vision&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20140905-the-women-with-super-human-vision&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;爲二色視覺的人做設計&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#爲二色視覺的人做設計&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;爲二色視覺的人做設計&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;爲二色視覺的人做設計&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;三色視覺佔人口大多數，物件、圖畫的設計，大多是爲三色視覺設計。不過，只要我們稍加留意，便能照顧到二色視覺者的需求。而且，這樣的設計，對於三色、四色視覺的人，也會更易理解、使用。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;技巧1-避免依賴色調表意（而是輔以形狀、紋理等元素）&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#技巧1-避免依賴色調表意（而是輔以形狀、紋理等元素）&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;技巧1 - 避免依賴色調表意（而是輔以形狀、紋理等元素）&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;技巧1 - 避免依賴色調表意（而是輔以形狀、紋理等元素）&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/traffic-lights-with-shapes.png&quot; alt=&quot;有形狀的交通燈，即使路人不能辨別紅綠，也能理解意思&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;模擬紅綠二色視覺中的行人交通燈。交通燈通常用綠、紅區分行、止，但如果信號加上形狀，即使路人不能辨認紅綠，也能通過辨認輪廓來識別信號。&lt;br&gt;源圖來源：&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ampel-Goettingen-14.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ampel-Goettingen-14.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;技巧2-避免依賴明度表意&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#技巧2-避免依賴明度表意&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;技巧2 - 避免依賴明度表意&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;技巧2 - 避免依賴明度表意&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;二色視覺、單色視覺的人色覺細胞類別比較少，因此對明度變化也沒那麼敏感。如果要使用明度區分（表達連續數量的常見手法），儘量使用明顯的明度差異。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;技巧3-發佈前預覽&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#技巧3-發佈前預覽&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;技巧3 - 發佈前預覽&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;技巧3 - 發佈前預覽&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/adobe-illustrator-proof-setup.png&quot; alt=&quot;Proof setup mode in Adobe Illustrator&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adobe Illustrator 有「色盲模式」，可以在發佈前預覽在二色視覺者眼中的設計效果。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;其中，Protanopia 是指沒有紅色感光細胞，Deuteranopia 是指沒有綠色感光細胞，臨牀症狀很相似，都是不易辨別紅綠。&lt;br&gt;如果足夠自信，甚至可以直接轉成灰度來看。如果一個設計轉成灰度圖都沒問題，則各類色覺的人都不會有困難。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我也嘗試做過一個實時的「非常規色覺模擬器」：&lt;a href=&quot;http://rgbx.shux.in&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;rgbx.shux.in&lt;/a&gt;，目前可以實時模擬二色視覺眼中的世界（在桌面機上支持Firefox和Chrome，Android上支持Firefox）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;延伸閱讀&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#延伸閱讀&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;延伸閱讀&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;延伸閱讀&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;【色彩感知】&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_vision&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Color vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://webvision.med.utah.edu/book/part-vii-color-vision/color-vision/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Color Vision by Peter Gouras&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;【非常規色覺】&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_blindness&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Wikipedia: Color Blindness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://designshack.net/articles/accessibility/tips-for-designing-for-colorblind-users/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Tips for Designing for Colorblind Users&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151012-what-is-colour/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jackathon #5: Read Journalism</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151005-read-journalism/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151005-read-journalism/</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 11:49:33 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;We’ll read Journalism books for Jackathon this weekend (October 10th or 11th).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reading list is compiled with input from within Initium Lab team and our colleagues.&lt;br&gt;Most on the list are in English; some are Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reading list covers books about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Journalism, such as the Verification Handbook for Investigative Reporting, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human bias, such as Daniel Kahneman’s Thinking: Fast and Slow,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storytelling, such as Robert McKee’s Story: Substance, Structure, Style and the Principles of Screenwriting,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing, such as Stephen King’s On Writing, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tradition of Journalism, such as The Elements of Journalism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll read one or more books in one day and share your learning with other participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like to participate, please fill in the form here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe&quot;&gt;http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll check the availability of potential participants and determine the final date, and notify everyone as soon as feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book list is as follows, categorized by theme.&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We’ll read Journalism books for Jackathon this weekend (October 10th or 11th).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reading list is compiled with input from within Initium Lab team and our colleagues.&lt;br&gt;Most on the list are in English; some are Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reading list covers books about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Journalism, such as the Verification Handbook for Investigative Reporting, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human bias, such as Daniel Kahneman’s Thinking: Fast and Slow,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Storytelling, such as Robert McKee’s Story: Substance, Structure, Style and the Principles of Screenwriting,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing, such as Stephen King’s On Writing, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tradition of Journalism, such as The Elements of Journalism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll read one or more books in one day and share your learning with other participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like to participate, please fill in the form here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://goo.gl/forms/74dOlnSqUe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll check the availability of potential participants and determine the final date, and notify everyone as soon as feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book list is as follows, categorized by theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Data-Journalism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Data-Journalism&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Data Journalism&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Data Journalism&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Data-Journalism-Handbook&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Data-Journalism-Handbook&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Data Journalism Handbook&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Data Journalism Handbook&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rich collection of cases demonstrating use of computer and statistical methods in Journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Verification-Handbook-for-Investigative-Reporting&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Verification-Handbook-for-Investigative-Reporting&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Verification Handbook for Investigative Reporting&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Verification Handbook for Investigative Reporting&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The book focuses on getting and cleaning data, with emphasis on user-generated information.&lt;br&gt;Availability&lt;br&gt;Free at &lt;a href=&quot;http://verificationhandbook.com/book2/chapter1.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://verificationhandbook.com/book2/chapter1.php&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Numbers-in-the-newsroom-using-math-and-statistics-in-News&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Numbers-in-the-newsroom-using-math-and-statistics-in-News&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Numbers in the newsroom: using math and statistics in News&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Numbers in the newsroom: using math and statistics in News&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The book mainly talks about application of basic Mathematics and Statistics in Journalism.&lt;br&gt;Availability&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;中国数据新闻工作坊培训手册&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#中国数据新闻工作坊培训手册&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;中国数据新闻工作坊培训手册&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;中国数据新闻工作坊培训手册&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Chinese book)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A compilation of a training workshop which taught the whole flow of Data Journalism.&lt;br&gt;Availability&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freely available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://djchina.org/2015/09/01/china-data-journalism-training-content/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://djchina.org/2015/09/01/china-data-journalism-training-content/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Signal-and-the-Noise&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Signal-and-the-Noise&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Signal and the Noise&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Signal and the Noise&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Written by Nate Silver, founder of FiveThirtyEight.com, an icon in Data Journalism. Introduces statistical thinking in daily lifes and the common mistakes made by media people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Thinking&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Thinking&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Thinking&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;A-Tradecraft-Primer-Structured-Analytic-Techniques-for-Improving-Intelligence-Analysis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#A-Tradecraft-Primer-Structured-Analytic-Techniques-for-Improving-Intelligence-Analysis&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;A Tradecraft Primer: Structured Analytic Techniques for Improving Intelligence Analysis&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A Tradecraft Primer: Structured Analytic Techniques for Improving Intelligence Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;It introduces the thinking techniques used by Central Intelligence Agency, published by CIA itself. Very practical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A data journalist is really like an intelligence analyst, who deals with a constant flow of unreliable and contradictory information, needs to deliver insights quickly, and faces pressures to favour certain conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freely available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/books-and-monographs/Tradecraft%20Primer-apr09.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/books-and-monographs/Tradecraft%20Primer-apr09.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Rationality-From-AI-to-Zombies&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Rationality-From-AI-to-Zombies&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Rationality: From AI to Zombies&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Rationality: From AI to Zombies&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;For people unfamiliar with cognitive psychology and decision theory, this could be an eye-opener. Written by a AI researcher and is really an edited collection of his blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Thinking-Fast-and-Slow-思考，快与慢&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Thinking-Fast-and-Slow-思考，快与慢&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Thinking, Fast and Slow / 思考，快与慢&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow / 思考，快与慢&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Detailed introduction into the study of (human) heuristics and biases, i.e., the predictable pattern of our thinking mistakes. The author is a psychologist who won a Nobel Economics prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Supplementary-Wikipedia-List-of-Cognitive-Biases&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Supplementary-Wikipedia-List-of-Cognitive-Biases&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;[Supplementary] Wikipedia: List of Cognitive Biases&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[Supplementary] Wikipedia: List of Cognitive Biases&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As journalists, it is crucial for us to be aware of our own biases.&lt;br&gt;This is A rather comprehensive list of cognitive biases, most of which have their own Wikipedia pages giving further details.&lt;br&gt;Freely available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Storytelling&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Storytelling&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Storytelling&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;Story-Substance-Structure-Style-and-the-Principles-of-Screenwriting&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Story-Substance-Structure-Style-and-the-Principles-of-Screenwriting&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Story: Substance, Structure, Style and the Principles of Screenwriting&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Story: Substance, Structure, Style and the Principles of Screenwriting&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Principles to make a story compelling from a screenplay writer’s perspective. The book also includes critiques and analysis on movies to illustrate its ideas. An inspiring book for nonfiction writers and journalists who are interested in writing features. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Art-and-Craft-of-Feature-Writing-Based-on-the-Wall-Street-Journal-Guide&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Art-and-Craft-of-Feature-Writing-Based-on-the-Wall-Street-Journal-Guide&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Art and Craft of Feature Writing: Based on the Wall Street Journal Guide&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Art and Craft of Feature Writing: Based on the Wall Street Journal Guide&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A step-by-step guide for turning out great articles. The book provides beginners with a systematic approach to feature writing and new tricks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Your-Screenplay-Sucks-100-Ways-to-Make-it-Great&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Your-Screenplay-Sucks-100-Ways-to-Make-it-Great&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Your Screenplay Sucks: 100 Ways to Make it Great&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Your Screenplay Sucks: 100 Ways to Make it Great&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Piecemeal advice about writing good screenplays that sell. May require some basic understanding of the structure and purposes of stories. Highly readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Writing&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Writing&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Writing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;Style-Lessons-in-Clarity-and-Grace&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Style-Lessons-in-Clarity-and-Grace&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Style: Lessons in Clarity and Grace&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Style: Lessons in Clarity and Grace&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A step by step guide to writing correctly and clearly. It is very practical and even somewhat applies to Chinese writing.&lt;br&gt;The older version is better, as they’re free from revisionist tampering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;On-Writing&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#On-Writing&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;On Writing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;On Writing&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Written by Stephen King, an American novelist. This is more a memoir than it’s a textbook, but a substantial part is about use of the English and writing (fiction, mostly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;On-Writing-Well&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#On-Writing-Well&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;On Writing Well&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;On Writing Well&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a book for journalism students as well as everyone to learn how to write clearly and elegantly (in English), covering kinds of genres and a wide range of  topics such as people, places, science, tech, business, sports, arts, etc. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Proust-and-the-Squid&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Proust-and-the-Squid&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Proust and the Squid&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Proust and the Squid&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This book is about the neurology of reading. How exactly does reading work? What can we know about reading from people with Dyslexia (unable to read, but intelligent otherwise) ? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Interviewing-and-Tradition-of-Journalism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Interviewing-and-Tradition-of-Journalism&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Interviewing and Tradition of Journalism&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Interviewing and Tradition of Journalism&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;在追问中逼近真实&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#在追问中逼近真实&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;在追问中逼近真实&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;在追问中逼近真实&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Chinese book)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Covers basic aspects of reporting about people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Elements-of-Journalism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Elements-of-Journalism&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Elements of Journalism&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Elements of Journalism&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A comprehensive description of (Western) journalists’ ideas about the core values of Journalism. (Spoiler: it’s “Objectiviy”.)&lt;br&gt;Availability&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20151005-read-journalism/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>整日做表沒思路？Google幫你開腦洞</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2015 16:06:19 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        &lt;p&gt;一個數據分析項目，往往始於摸索一張龐大而陌生的數據表格。嘗試畫些簡易圖表是啟發思路的好辦法，但這絕非易事──想想有多少種圖表：直方圖柱狀圖餅圖折線圖雷達圖……若選取不同的列來分析，每種圖表又有多達幾十種畫法。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Sheets 最近推出了一項新功能 Explore，或許能成為探索陌生數據的第一步。Google 介紹稱，Explore 能根據表格內容自動生成盡可能多的圖表，還順帶做些數據分析，挖掘數據的關聯和趨勢[1]。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore 的使用方法很簡單，一次點擊就能自動出圖，不時還會附上（它認為）有趣的發現，例如列舉最大值和最小值等。&lt;/p&gt;
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;一個數據分析項目，往往始於摸索一張龐大而陌生的數據表格。嘗試畫些簡易圖表是啟發思路的好辦法，但這絕非易事──想想有多少種圖表：直方圖柱狀圖餅圖折線圖雷達圖……若選取不同的列來分析，每種圖表又有多達幾十種畫法。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Sheets 最近推出了一項新功能 Explore，或許能成為探索陌生數據的第一步。Google 介紹稱，Explore 能根據表格內容自動生成盡可能多的圖表，還順帶做些數據分析，挖掘數據的關聯和趨勢[1]。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore 的使用方法很簡單，一次點擊就能自動出圖，不時還會附上（它認為）有趣的發現，例如列舉最大值和最小值等。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/explore.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Demo of google explore sheet&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但，作為一個每天使用 Google Sheets 超過8小時的人，面對橫空出世的 Explore，欣喜之餘不免有些懷疑，Explore 真的有這麼神？碰巧 Initium Lab 最近出了&lt;a href=&quot;http://salary360.initiumlab.com/?from=initiumlab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;香港工資測試遊戲&lt;/a&gt;[2]，遊戲使用 2011 年香港人口普查的公開數據[3]，我從中選取了三張表格來測試 Explore 的實用性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-呈現數據：自動選重點出圖&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1-呈現數據：自動選重點出圖&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;1.呈現數據：自動選重點出圖&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1.呈現數據：自動選重點出圖&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;下圖是一張很常見的表格[4]，要點明確、容易讀懂。Explore 基於表格裏的35項數據自動做出了十張圖，動用了柱狀圖、餅圖、折線圖和堆疊折線圖四種形態。有的圖表下方會出現「一句話總結」，基本都戳中要點。對這種經過預處理的表格而言，Explore 的確能提供不少呈現數據的思路。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;用 Explore 呈現簡單表格的數據&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-探索數據：幫忙挖掘潛在關聯&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2-探索數據：幫忙挖掘潛在關聯&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;2.探索數據：幫忙挖掘潛在關聯&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2.探索數據：幫忙挖掘潛在關聯&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;一些初看沒什麼亮點的表格，往往藏着大新聞。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我選取的第二個例子[5][6]，統計了香港各區年齡超過65歲的人口比例、慣用廣東話的人口比例和慣用英語的人口比例。一看到這張表，最自然的反應就是，人口年齡和慣用語言之間會不會有關係呢？來看 Explore 有何洞見。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在一秒畫出的十幾張圖表裏，Explore 認為最有趣的發現是，慣用廣東話的人口比例每增加10%，慣用英語的人口比例就會下降7%，這和我們的常識相吻合。雖然在這個例子中 Explore 沒有給出我最想知道的答案，但它兩兩比較了表中的三個變量，幫忙發掘潛在的關聯。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;用 Explore 探索數據潛在的關聯&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-結構扁平的表格：請和-pivot-table-一起使用&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3-結構扁平的表格：請和-pivot-table-一起使用&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;3.結構扁平的表格：請和 pivot table 一起使用&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3.結構扁平的表格：請和 pivot table 一起使用&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;處理大批量數據，一般離不開結構扁平的表格，如下圖所示，這類表格信息龐雜、沒有重點。我選取了2011年全港居民的月收入統計來做試驗[7]，這張表格有超過20萬項數據。此時 Explore 就有些力不從心了，它能做的只是發現某列數字的最大或最小值，或是統計不同字符串在某列出現的次數及比例。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在原表格的基礎上做出 pivot table (又稱樞紐分析表，是一種基於原始表格的動態表格，便於將大量的數據集縮小、或分析數據之間的關係) 以後，Explore 能給出新的呈現，做「篩選」和「排序」時，圖表也會實時變化。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;當 Explore 遇到扁平化表格，最好先使用 pivot table 選出要點&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;總之，Google Sheets 新功能 Explore 能在最短的時間內羅列出盡可能多的圖表和分析，最適合在探索數據之初，拿來開開腦洞、找找頭緒。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;資料來源：&lt;br&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/docs/answer/6280499?hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Quickly get insights on a spreadsheet using Explore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://salary360.initiumlab.com/?from=initiumlab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;十八區人工大比拼，你份量攞第幾？&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;[3] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;香港政府統計處 2011香港人口普查&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/main-table/E103.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;2001年、2006年及2011年按房屋類型劃分的家庭住戶數目&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;[5] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/main-table/A301.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;2011年按區議會選區及慣用語言劃分的五歲及以上的人口&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;[6] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.census2011.gov.hk/tc/main-table/A303.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;2011年按區議會選區、性別及年齡組別劃分的人口&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;[7] &lt;a href=&quot;http://gazetteer.hk/#/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Gazetteer HK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150930-google-sheets-explore/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>React in One Hour</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150925-react-in-1-hour-cuhk/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150925-react-in-1-hour-cuhk/</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 09:02:13 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        Andy Shu, news engineer with Initium Lab, gave a brief tutorial about ReactJS, the Web UI library from Facebook, in Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK) on 18 September 2015. The event was organized by the Open Innovation Lab of CUHK.
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Andy Shu, news engineer with Initium Lab, gave a brief tutorial about ReactJS, the Web UI library from Facebook,&lt;br&gt;in Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK) on 18 September 2015. The event was organized by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/cuhkoil&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Open Innovation Lab&lt;/a&gt; of CUHK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy introduced the basics of React and demonstrated making a simple quiz app from the ground up with React.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the video recoding of the tutorial:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;    &lt;iframe id=&quot;player&quot; type=&quot;text/html&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;390&quot; src=&quot;https://youtube.com/embed/_fqf7tGWBvE?html5=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;    &lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The video is also available on &lt;a href=&quot;http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XMTM0NDg0Mzg5Mg==.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Youku&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Key-time-points&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Key-time-points&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Key time points&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Key time points&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;00:00 - Introduction to Initium Lab and the Speaker&lt;br&gt;05:02 - What is React&lt;br&gt;16:21 - Necessary packages and tools&lt;br&gt;25:07 - Coding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the tutorial, a Q&amp;amp;A session was held (not recorded due to technical issues). Afterwards, a few participants stayed for further discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Supporting-Materials&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Supporting-Materials&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Supporting Materials&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Supporting Materials&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://tryreact.initiumlab.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;tryreact.initiumlab.com&lt;/a&gt; for supporting materials used in the tutorial, such as the &lt;code&gt;quiz.html&lt;/code&gt;, from which you can follow Andy step by step. Intermediate coding samples are also available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;How-to-pick-up-JavaScript&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#How-to-pick-up-JavaScript&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;How to pick up JavaScript&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How to pick up JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about how he learnt JavaScript in a short period of time, Andy recommended the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codecademy.com/tracks/javascript&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;JavaScript track of Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; for absolute beginners, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596517748.do&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;JavaScript: The Good Parts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; for a deeper look into the language, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9781118026694.do&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Professional JavaScript for Web Developers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; for more comprehensive understanding. He also said frequent practice was crucial to learning. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Errata&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Errata&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Errata&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Errata&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under JavaScript strict mode, &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; in functions should be &lt;code&gt;undefined&lt;/code&gt;, not &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br&gt;One might have the impression that in the source code, elements like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; are just native HTML elements. That is inaccurate. In fact, they are Virtual DOM elements, implemented by React.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150925-react-in-1-hour-cuhk/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jackathon #3 -- Read a data science book in 8 hours</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 03:57:13 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        Jackathon is short for “Journalism-Hackathon”. At Initium Lab, we aim to push limits of Journalism with Technology. We hold regular Jackathons to advance our knowledge and skills in using new technology for obtaining data, analysing information, and reporting. This week, the goal for each participant is to read one the the 60 Data Science books collected by KDnuggets within 8 hours. 
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;video controls poster=&quot;/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/jackathon3-timelapse-poster.png&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;source src=&quot;/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/jackathon3-timelapse.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;source src=&quot;/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/jackathon3-timelapse.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  Sorry, you browser does not support HTML5 video.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video is also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/zFeSh2W1_C8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XMTM0MzM1MjEwMA==.html?from=y1.7-2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Youku&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;What-did-we-do&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#What-did-we-do&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;What did we do?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What did we do?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jackathon is short for “Journalism-Hackathon”. At Initium Lab, we aim to push limits of Journalism with Technology. We hold regular Jackathons to advance our knowledge and skills in using new technology for obtaining data, analysing information, and reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, the goal for each participant is to read one the the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;60 Data Science books collected by KDnuggets&lt;/a&gt; within 8 hours.&lt;br&gt;Participants could pick one or two books to finish reading in 8 hours and present findings / insights to the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;What-are-the-books&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#What-are-the-books&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;What are the books?&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What are the books?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/data-science-books-graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;A network of the Data Science books on the recommendation list. A cloud of inter-connected dots&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fig: Network of 60 books. Blue – book; Red – author; Yellow – key term&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have organised the book list into a structured form and &lt;a href=&quot;https://kumu.io/hupili/60-free-data-science-book#60-free-data-science-book&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;visualized the network on kumu.io&lt;/a&gt;. Books are associated with authors and terms. Multiple books may share an author or key terms. In this way, books are connected to each other in one way or the other. With graph visualization, we find several clusters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard-core machine learning including deep academic results; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practitioner’s guide including several soft introductory books; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those in-between.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every participant of Jackathon #3 finds a suitable book for themselves. For a complete list, you can download &lt;a href=&quot;CSV of 60+ data science books: https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1U28nb1z9PsXNzNe_YtfPYYUdhH7_YfjEz6L0Z_wpxzM/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;the CSV file&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;To see how we produces this network visualisation, checkout &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hupili/60-data-science-book-visualisation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;this repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Introduction-to-Data-Science&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Introduction-to-Data-Science&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Introduction to Data Science&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Introduction to Data Science&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kate, who was from a non-technical background, picked &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Data Science&lt;/em&gt;. The book is useful to equip one with basic Data Science knowledge. The main take-away for Kate was a better understanding of a Data Scientist’s workflow. It turns out that a Data Scientist is not only responsible for “data analysis” but also works on various positions in the whole pipeline including problem identification, data collection, and data visualisation, etc. It is worth noting that this book uses R (a widely used programming language in the Statistics community) to explain Data Science.&lt;br&gt;If you intend to learn R, this book may be a good starting point. Otherwise, you can pick a book using another language (say Python), or a book that is not language dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;The-Elements-of-Data-Analytic-Style&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Elements-of-Data-Analytic-Style&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Elements of Data Analytic Style&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Elements of Data Analytic Style&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Belinda finds the book &lt;em&gt;The Elements of Data Analytic Style&lt;/em&gt; also suitable for beginners. Chapter 3 (on tidying data), are good readings for a Data Scientist’s assistants, while Chapter 9 (on written analysis), teaches useful soft skills. One effective way to read the book is to scan the Table-Of-Content. The ideas are mostly well communicated via section headers. One doesn’t have to read the whole book for the key ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Think-Bayes-Bayesian-Statistics-Made-Simple&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Think-Bayes-Bayesian-Statistics-Made-Simple&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Think Bayes: Bayesian Statistics Made Simple&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Think Bayes: Bayesian Statistics Made Simple&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;From what Carlson summarises, this book is a practitioner’s guide to statistics. The book deprives lengthy and boring mathematical derivations from a usual first book in statistics and shows you examples/ codes directly. The examples picked in this book is counter-intuitive but demonstrates the power of probability/ statistics knowledge very well. Some well known probability “paradox” includes “Monte Hall problem”, “Locomotive problem” and “Price is Right problem”. The book is case driven. A recommended way of reading is to combine thorough introduction from Wikipedia and code samples from this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Think-Stats-Exploratory-Data-Analysis-in-Python&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Think-Stats-Exploratory-Data-Analysis-in-Python&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Think Stats: Exploratory Data Analysis in Python&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Think Stats: Exploratory Data Analysis in Python&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frank went through &lt;em&gt;Think Stats: Exploratory Data Analysis in Python&lt;/em&gt;, written by Allen B. Downey, who also wrote &lt;em&gt;Think Bayes&lt;/em&gt;. “If you have never studied statistics, I think this book is a good place to start,” the author said, “And if you have taken a traditional statistics class, I hope this book will help repair the damage.”&lt;br&gt;This book introduces statistical analysis concepts along with Python implementations, including data importing and cleaning, single and multivariable explorations, pair-wise explorations, estimation, and hypothesis testing.&lt;br&gt;If you want to apply your Python skill in data analysis, this book is a practical handbook for you with no redundant words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Introduction-to-D3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Introduction-to-D3&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Introduction to D3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Introduction to D3&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Andy skimmed two books, &lt;em&gt;D3 Tips and Tricks&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Interactive Data Visualization for the Web&lt;/em&gt;, as well as the original paper that launched D3. D3 stands for Data-Driven Documents, which is a popular “language” (more precisely a Javascript library) for modern data visualisation in the browser. Andy recommends one start with the paper &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vis.stanford.edu/papers/d3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;D3: Data Driven Documents&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt;  written by the D3 creator. The paper explains the design rationales behind D3 very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the two books, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books/1230000000345/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Interactive Data Visualization for the Web&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt; is recommended for beginners because it includes elementary knowledges about HTML all the way to Javascript with a step-by-step guide through the basics of D3. In comparison, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com/D3-Tips-and-Tricks&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;D3 Tips and Tricks&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt;  more akin to a reference book, is recommended for more experienced users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a practice, Andy took two hours to make an incomplete imitation of the default visualization of GapMinder (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gapminder.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://www.gapminder.org&lt;/a&gt;) with D3, which illustrated the relationship between wealth and health since 1800. The source code is hosted at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andyshuxin/d3play&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;https://github.com/andyshuxin/d3play&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Natural-Language-Processing-with-Python&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Natural-Language-Processing-with-Python&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Natural Language Processing with Python&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Natural Language Processing with Python&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ronald have years of experience with image processing and machine learning. He chooses the book &lt;em&gt;Natural Language Processing with Python&lt;/em&gt; in order to get some basic knowledge of Natural Language Processing, which may be useful in his recent projects. The book covers NLP principles and practices by showing examples with a Python library called &lt;code&gt;nltk&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;nlkt&lt;/code&gt; is regarded as the defacto standard of NLP in Python, from triping HTML to tokenizing/ tagging sentences. It supports 50+ languages including Chinese. This book is a good fit if you want to deal with unstructured texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Social-Media-Mining-An-Introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Social-Media-Mining-An-Introduction&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Social Media Mining: An Introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Social Media Mining: An Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This book is compiled from a series of lecture notes, which makes it self-contained. According to Tiffany, “Reading this book is like finishing a whole semester’s course in one day right before final exam”. Before diving into social media mining, the book paves the way by introducing fundamentals of graph theory. There are several widely discussed problems related with graphs and social networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network measures. One important concept called “centrality” is used to measure the importance of a node in a network. There are many different metrics that characterise different aspects of importance in a network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network models. More precisely speaking, those are called “network generation models”. Say, whether a new node in the network connects to a uniformly random node or picks the node with higher degree? Graphs generated by different models exhibit different characteristics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community. Community is group of closely knitted nodes. Discovering community leads to many applications. One example is the book network plotted at the beginning of this blog post. You can easily identify similar books in this way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information diffusion. In advertisement scheduling, one can find more effective seed users if the diffusion process is known. There are many models to characterize information diffusion: does the crowd exhibit a herd behaviour? does the adoption probability depend on ratio of existing users (innovation) or not (epidemics)?.. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Influence and homophily. This is the graph theoretic characterisation of the “chicken-and-egg” common knowledge: friends become similar; similar people become friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Real-Time-Big-Data-Analytics-Emerging-Architecture&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Real-Time-Big-Data-Analytics-Emerging-Architecture&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Real-Time Big Data Analytics: Emerging Architecture&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Real-Time Big Data Analytics: Emerging Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another book read by Belinda is &lt;em&gt;Real-Time Big Data Analytics: Emerging Architecture&lt;/em&gt;. This book is more like a guide for executives. It discusses why we need real-time analysis, the challenges, current tool chain and proposed one solution stack. The key objective for real-time analysis is to combine batch and streaming processing. An overview of the proposed architecture reveals four layers. The data layer stores raw data, in heterogeneous or even unstructured format. The analytics layer addresses data buffering and environment (development/ production) isolation issues. The integration layer contains a rule engine and other services that connect data scientists with end users. The decision layer involve end users and provide friendly UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;References-and-further-readings&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#References-and-further-readings&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;References and further readings&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;References and further readings&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KDnuggets, “60+ Free Books on Big Data, Data Science, Data Mining, Machine Learning, Python, R, and more”, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://www.kdnuggets.com/2015/09/free-data-science-books.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;O’Reilly Atlas Reader, &lt;a href=&quot;http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;http://chimera.labs.oreilly.com/books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150922-jackathon3-review/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legco Matrix Brief (English)</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150916-legco-eng/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150916-legco-eng/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 04:29:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        We analysed the voting data of the Hong Kong Legislative Council. This is the English version of the motion graphic and digest of the news report.
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We have promised you an English version of our video about the voting patterns of Hong Kong Legislative Council.&lt;br&gt;And here it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video controls poster=&quot;/blog/20150916-legco-eng/legco_animation_poster.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;source src=&quot;/blog/20150916-legco-eng/legco_animation_EngSub.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;source src=&quot;/blog/20150916-legco-eng/legco_animation_EngSub.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  Sorry, your browser does not support HTML5 video.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/video&gt;&lt;br&gt;The video is also available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CExoTvKuXSw&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://v.youku.com/v_show/id_XMTM0MzM5NzQwOA==.html?from=y1.7-1.2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Youku&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also translated the sections of news reports explaining the mysteries mentioned in the video, as follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Why-Starry-Lee-voted-against-herself&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Why-Starry-Lee-voted-against-herself&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Why Starry Lee voted against herself&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why Starry Lee voted against herself&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The diagonal shows how each legislator support their own motions. The more supportive they are, the brighter the block. However, there is one outlier on this bright line. Starry Lee Wai-king, chairwoman of Democratic Alliance for the Betterment and Progress of Hong Kong (DAB) and member of the Executive Council, voted against herself 7 times from February 20 to February 21, 2012. During this time, she proposed several amendments to the draft of Stamp Duty Bill but she voted against these amendments herself. Lee replied via her assistant and explained that, she was serving as the president to the committee responsible for revising the bill, and the committee members decided that she, the president, should propose the revisions for them. As DAB opposed those bills, she chose to vote against amendments technically proposed by her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;Why-Poon-Siu-ping-is-more-popular-on-the-opposite-camp&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Why-Poon-Siu-ping-is-more-popular-on-the-opposite-camp&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Why Poon Siu-ping is more popular on the opposite camp&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why Poon Siu-ping is more popular on the opposite camp&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the voting records, no motion amendment from Poon Siu-ping got passed. However, his motion on Occupational Safety, through secret ballot, has been adopted. Poon replied to us that there is no fundamental disagreement between Hong Kong Federation of Trade Unions (FTU) and Federation of Hong Kong and Kowloon Labour Unions (FLU), as FTU is also on pro-establishment camp. However, Poon didn’t think it would be easy to gain FTU’s support: “To improve labour rights and benefits, one has to change the consistently business-oriented operating environment, but many legislators of functional constituency represents business interests and naturally they are unlikely to support motions protecting labour rights.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma Ngok, chairman of Department of Government and Public Administration, Chinese University of Hong Kong, thought pan-democrats have been in mutual restraint since 2012. He said, “First of all, on class position, Civic Party and Democratic Party are moving forward grass-root sector, and they are not much different from the grass-root pan-democracy parties. For instance, a decade ago many pan-democracy parties were doubtful about universal retirement protection, while today all pan-democracy parties support it”. Another reason is the limited power of the Legislative Council. “When debating about grassroot-related motions, which are predictably impossible to pass, many parties would rather follow the trend to avoid controversies”, said Ma.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma Ngok explained that,  the reason why Poon Sui-ping, Kwok Wai-keung and Tang Ka-piu were unsupported by pro-establishment camp was probably that functional constituency has long been unwelcoming the labour issues. “Nearly half of the 35 members in functional constituency are in business sector, and some legislators from professional constituencies also tend to business sector. Their attachment to the sector interests makes labour issues hard to gain support.”, said Ma.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150916-legco-eng/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>可視化火了 盲人怎麼辦</title>
      <link>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/</link>
      <guid>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 13:39:43 GMT</pubDate>
      <description>
      
        作爲新聞人，我們可以怎樣照顧盲人的信息需求呢？
      
      </description>
      
      <content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/news-related-disabilities.png&quot; alt=&quot;中國有視力殘障1040萬，香港人口才710萬，上海常住人口2302萬。&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;中國有五百萬盲人&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note1&quot;&gt;[註1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;， 接近香港的總人口。 加上弱視，總數超過一千二百萬&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note2&quot;&gt;[註2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;盲人走丟是舊聞，盲貓失蹤纔是新聞：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;經濟日報：偷貓賊出沒 書店盲貓福仔被盜&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;文匯報：黑褸賊書局偷盲貓 片段網上瘋傳&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;東方日報：盲貓「福仔」被尋回　主人喜與愛貓重聚&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;蘋果日報：被偷5日　疑賊人送往愛協　盲貓「福仔」回家了&lt;br&gt;等等……&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;a id=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;盲人也可以用電腦，也會讀新聞。他們看不見，但是聽得到，他們上網用讀屏軟件，屏幕上的字詞，一個個去聽。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;現在新聞界，流行信息圖，把大段文字轉化成圖表，方便讀者閱讀。 但正所謂君之蜜糖，彼之砒霜，普通人愛看的信息圖、可視化，對於盲人的讀屏軟件，則是巨大的障礙。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;那麼，作爲新聞人，我們可以怎樣照顧盲人的信息需求呢？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;盲人怎麼讀新聞&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#盲人怎麼讀新聞&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;盲人怎麼讀新聞&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;盲人怎麼讀新聞&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;普通人閱讀靠視覺，是「並行」的——你看一眼網頁界面，就知道菜單在哪、內容在哪、哪個是鏈接、哪個可以點。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;聽覺是「串行」的，一個盲人如果想「讀完」一個網頁，要讓讀屏軟件從第一個元素（按鈕、菜單選項等）讀起，然後一個一個元素讀下去。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果想體驗讀屏軟件，在 OS X 或 iPhone 下，可以試用 「VoiceOver」， 這是蘋果內置的讀屏軟件。 閉上眼睛，嘗試一下盲人使用電子產品的方式，試試做一些平常覺得輕而易舉的事情：瀏覽網頁、發發微博，等等。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows 可以下載「爭渡讀屏」， Android用戶可以試試內置的Talkback。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;給圖像加上詳細的文字描述（alt）&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#給圖像加上詳細的文字描述（alt）&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;給圖像加上詳細的文字描述（alt）&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;給圖像加上詳細的文字描述（alt）&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;讀屏軟件讀不了數據圖表，於是我們要爲視障讀者撰寫圖像的替代文字描述，具體而言，就是HTML中IMG元素的alt屬性。 對於讀屏軟件的用戶，alt的內容會被完整讀出。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;替代說明應該儘可能簡短，但是能夠讓沒有看到圖的讀者都能理解內容。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;比如，不要寫「中國GDP數據可視化」，而是寫「中國GDP近年快速增長，2000年爲1.2千億美元，2005年爲2.3千億，2010年爲5.9千億。」&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;替代說明有個額外的好處：利於搜索引擎處理。搜索引擎蒐集數據，是靠大量「爬蟲」程序，一個網頁一個網頁地檢索內容。爬蟲和盲人一樣，只能「看到」文字，無法閱讀圖像，所以，如果一篇文章的重要信息由圖像呈現，又沒有替代說明，則搜索引擎也看不到這些信息，從而讓用戶更難發現你的文章。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;數據可聽化（Sonification）&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#數據可聽化（Sonification）&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;數據可聽化（Sonification）&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;數據可聽化（Sonification）&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;可聽化是與可視化相似的概念。我們做可視化，是因爲大多數人對數字沒有直覺，難以理解，但是我們對顏色、尺寸、方向有直覺——於是，將數字轉化爲圖像，能夠讓讀者更容易解讀數據。對於依賴聽力的盲人，我們則可以用「可聽化」。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;聲音可以操縱的變量有：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;響度，即大聲還是小聲；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;頻率，即高音還是低音；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;音色，即泛音的構成；&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;長度，即很長還是很短。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果將數據與上述一個或幾個變量連接，就能構成一個「可聽化」作品。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一個例子是&lt;a href=&quot;http://listen.hatnote.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Listen to Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;。它會實時監測維基百科的改動，然後將每次改動化爲聲音，改動越大，聲音頻率越高；音色代表改動類型——敲擊樂是增訂，絃樂是刪減。這個作品本身對盲人可能用處不大，但是這個技術思路可以用在新聞報道上。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;數據可觸化&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#數據可觸化&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;數據可觸化&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;數據可觸化&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;盲人不止有聽覺，也有觸覺。如果我們將數據化作實際存在的物體，則盲人可以通過觸覺感知。在這個方向，探索的人比較少，偶爾見到零星的嘗試。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;比如，西班牙記者 Samuel Granados López &lt;a href=&quot;http://cargocollective.com/samuelgranados/Lego-cartogram&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;用樂高積木做過一個地圖&lt;/a&gt;，用以標識美洲各國的移民流入、流出量：&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://payload230.cargocollective.com/1/14/463324/6918937/IMG_1014.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;一塊一人多高的底板，垂直放置。上面用樂高積木拼出了美洲各國，各個國家的突起程度並不相同，移民量越大的國家，越突出。&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;展望：數據新聞無障礙&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#展望：數據新聞無障礙&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;展望：數據新聞無障礙&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;展望：數據新聞無障礙&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;過去，新聞的主要呈現方式是文字，輔以照片、插圖。盲人用了讀屏軟件，也能獲取大部分的信息。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;現在，「數據新聞」興起，信息圖、可視化流行，非數據的新聞報道也講求「視覺」「互動」。 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;新聞人考慮的大多是報道網頁在手機上能不能看、用觸屏好不好控制，不太考慮盲人用戶能否閱讀、色盲用戶會否迷惑、殘障用戶能否使用。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們在呈現方式上發足狂奔之時，不應該忽略少數有特別需求的用戶。 有的用戶看不到屏幕、有的用戶用不了鼠標，他們仍然有信息需求，仍然可以是我們的讀者。 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我們在製作每條新聞報道的時候，不止要考慮如何讓大多數用戶迅速理解，也要考慮如何保證每個用戶對新聞內容能有最基本的了解。&lt;br&gt;從今天開始，請給你的信息圖加上alt吧！&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;數據來源&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;note1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs230/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;世界衛生組織&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;note2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zgmx.org.cn/html/default/4/NewsDefault-47618.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;中國盲人協會&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;殘疾人口數據來自： &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdpf.org.cn/sjzx/cjrgk/201206/t20120626_387581.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;殘疾人聯合會&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;上海人口數據來自： &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shrkjsw.gov.cn/dr/stat/ssh/2011823/000000003500041001134458916.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;上海市人口和計劃生育委員會&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;香港人口數據來自： &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.censtatd.gov.hk/hkstat/sub/sp150.jsp?productCode=B1120017&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;香港政府統計處&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content:encoded>
      
      <comments>http://initiumlab.com/blog/blog/20150901-data-journalism-for-the-blind/#disqus_thread</comments>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
